<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the Church of England from the foul aspersions of schism and heresie unjustly cast upon her by the Church of Rome. In two parts</title>
            <author>Altham, Michael, 1633-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2935A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152538</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152538)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2301:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the Church of England from the foul aspersions of schism and heresie unjustly cast upon her by the Church of Rome. In two parts</title>
                  <author>Altham, Michael, 1633-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30, [2], 5-50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.H. for Luke Meredith, at the King's Head at the west end of St. Paul's Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII. [1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Michael Altham. -- Wing (CD ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>"A vindication of the Church of England ... Part II." has separate title page, pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Congregational Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152538:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Church of England</hi> From the foul Aſperſions of Schiſm and Hereſie Unjuſtly caſt upon Her by <hi>The Church of Rome.</hi> In Two Parts.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>—After the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers, believing all things which are written in the Law and the Prophets. <bibl>
                           <hi>Acts 24.14.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152538:2"/>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Ex Aedib. <hi>Lambeth.</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Nov.</hi> 30. 1686.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Guil. Needham</hi> RR<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto P. ac D. D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc. <hi>Cantuar.</hi> a Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>Advertiſements of Books lately Printed.</head>
                  <p>BIſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Opuſcula.</hi> The Meaſures of Friendſhip. With Five Letters to perſons changed and tempted to a change in their Religion. To which is now added his Moral Demonſtration, proving that the Religion of <hi>J. Chriſt</hi> is from God. Price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two Treatiſes: The Firſt concerning <hi>Reproaching</hi> and <hi>Cenſure;</hi> The Second, An Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Serjeant</hi>'s <hi>Sure-Footing.</hi> To which are annexed, <hi>Three Sermons</hi> Preached upon ſeveral Occaſions; and very uſefull for theſe Times. By the late Learned and Reverend <hi>William Faulkner,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  <p>Some Queries to Proteſtants Anſwered, and an Explanation of the Roman Catholicks Belief in four great Points conſidered. 1. Concerning their <hi>Church.</hi> 2. Their <hi>Worſhip.</hi> 3. <hi>Juſtification.</hi> 4. <hi>Civil Government.</hi> Price ſtitch'd 6 <hi>d.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Creed of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth; Or, a Proſpect of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry taken from that Authentick Record. With ſhort Notes.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152538:2"/>
                  <head>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
                     <p>THere is nothing more frequent among thoſe of the Romiſh Communion, than to charge thoſe of the Reformation with the guilt of Schiſm and Hereſie. They blacken us with thoſe odious names of Schiſmatick and Heretick; and though we do publickly declare our abhorrence of thoſe Crimes, and diſavow both the name and thing; yet muſt we be repreſented as ſuch, and under that Character be expoſed to the World.</p>
                     <p>Whether this Charge be juſt or unjuſt, will appear by the ſequel of this Diſcourſe. But whetherſoever it be, certain it is, that it is generally taken for granted among them, that we are ſuch. A late Authour of theirs, in anſwer to this Queſtion, <hi>Why are you a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick?</hi> having (as he thinks) charged theſe Crimes home upon Proteſtants, at length, ſumms up his harangue in theſe words, <hi>p. 12.</hi> 
                        <q rend="inline">Now it being impoſſible for Proteſtants to excuſe, much leſs to juſtifie their manifeſt Schiſm, to what purpoſe is it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into debate with them about particular points of Doctrine? As long as the Charge of Schiſm ſubſiſts, uncleared by them, and this Schiſm grounded on pretended dangerous errors in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, being Schiſmaticks, they are Hereticks too, and ſo condemned by themſelves, and conſequently not to be hearkned to, when they will raiſe particular Controverſies; ſince this one ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Controverſie determines againſt them all particular debates.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>And now who would not think that here were a fair end put to all debates between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and us? for if we be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Schiſmaticks, and our Schiſm ſo manifeſt that it will admit
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152538:3"/>of no excuſe, much leſs of any juſtification; then this Gentleman is in the right, that it is to little purpoſe to enter into debate with us about particular points of Doctrine. But if we be not only Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks but Hereticks too, then ought we not to be hearkned to in any particular Controverſie whatſoever.</p>
                     <p>But if this Gentleman ſhould happen to be miſtaken in all this, and that we are neither Schiſmaticks nor Hereticks; but that our Separation from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not only excuſable, but ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable too; being grounded, not on pretended, but really dangerous errors, not in the Catholick Church, but in the particular Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> then I hope we may ſtand upon even ground with them, and be admitted to debate the matter in difference between us; which if we be, as they hitherto have done, ſo I hope they always will find us ready to ſtand the ſhock, and make good our ground.</p>
                     <p>As for the Crimes they charge us with, we have as great, it may be a greater abhorrence of them than they have; let them draw them in the moſt frightfull ſhapes imaginable, let them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them under the moſt black and diſmal Character that is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet can they not repreſent them worſe than we already think of them. So far are we from owning either the name or thing. We believe they are moſt horrible ſins, ſo dangerous and deſtructive that Men are thereby out of the ordinary ways and means of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they tear in pieces the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, and are an inlet to all thoſe miſchiefs that do or can happen to the Church of God. And after ſuch a Declaration as this, can we be thought to believe our ſelves guilty of them?</p>
                     <p>We are thus far agreed, that Schiſm and Hereſie are dangerous ſins, deſtructive of the peace and order, the well-being at leaſt, if not the Being of God's Church; and ſuch ſins as without a true and timely Repentance will unavoidably and eternally ruine thoſe that are guilty of them. It will therefore greatly concern all Perſons, as well Papiſts as Proteſtants, to clear themſelves of theſe Crimes.</p>
                     <p>To wipe off this ſcandal, which is ſo unjuſtly thrown upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe in Communion with her, is the deſign of theſe Papers. And to effect this, I know no better way than by laying open the nature and true notion of theſe two Crimes, <hi>viz.</hi> Schiſm and Hereſie; and then conſidering to whom they are applicable. This I ſhall endeavour to doe as briefly and as plainly as I can. But becauſe they are different Crimes, to avoid confuſion, I ſhall conſider them apart; and in the firſt place ſhall begin with that of Schiſm.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152538:3"/>
                     <head>SECT. I. <hi>Of Schiſm in general.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE word Schiſm in its original ſignification imports no more but only a Diviſion, Rent, or Breach; and is more properly applicable unto things than Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. I could, if it were neceſſary, produce ſeveral inſtances out of prophane Authours, where it is thus uſed; but waving theſe, I ſhall at preſent offer you only one inſtance, in which our Bleſſed Saviour thus applies the word. <hi>No Man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>puts a piece of new Cloth into an old Garment, for that which is put in taketh from the Garment,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>and the Rent,</hi> or Breach, <hi>is made worſe,</hi> Matt. 9.16.</p>
                     <p>When therefore we meet with this word applied to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, it is not properly, but Metaphorically uſed; importing a Diviſion among them, occaſioned by miſunderſtanding, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of opinions, diſcontent, or otherwiſe. Now foraſmuch as every Diviſion ſuppoſes an Unity, and that Unity broken; it cannot be applied to ſingle Perſons, but Perſons in Society, who live in Communion with one another, and are obliged ſo to doe by ſome common Ties and Obligations.</p>
                     <p>There are two great and eminent Societies in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical; and both theſe are the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Schiſm; <hi>i. e.</hi> they are both liable to have their Unity broken, their Peace diſturbed, and their Communion rent and ſhattered, if not diſſolved by evil Members.</p>
                     <p>As for the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the Civil State, when, by ſome factious and ſeditious Members, Feuds and Animoſities are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; and by that means the Unity is broken, and the Body divided into ſeveral Parties; then doth it labour under a dangerous Schiſm. We have an eminent inſtance hereof in Holy Writ;
<note place="margin">1 Kings 12. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> 
                        <hi>The Ten Tribes of Iſrael being violently rent and torn from the Houſe of David, in the days of Reboboam.</hi> Nor are we without as great an inſtance in our own memories, and in this Kingdom. But this is not the Schiſm we are now to treat of.</p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152538:4"/>
                     <p>As for the other, <hi>viz.</hi> the Eccleſiaſtical State, it is no leſs ſubject to it than the Civil. And hath been ſo much peſtered therewith, that from the firſt foundation thereof untill this day, we can hardly name a time, I am ſure no long time, in which it did ever enjoy perfect Peace and Tranquillity. How much the Church of God is broken and divided, and crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled into parties and factions at this day, is but too apparent; and who can look upon thoſe wounds and bruiſes which ſhe hath received thereby, without melting into tears, and being overwhelmed with grief and ſorrow? How great and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſin is, who have been the occaſion thereof, they will one day find, and ſeverely ſuffer for it, unleſs with the tears of true and unfeigned Repentance, they do in time waſh off the guilt of it, and by that means find favour with God. I pray God give us all grace ſeriouſly to conſider what ſhare we have in the Church's Sufferings, and in our ſeveral places to make it our great and only buſineſs to reſtore Peace and Unity thereunto.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. II. <hi>Of Schiſm in the Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THIS is the Crime which by our Adverſaries is laid to our charge, and this is that which I have undertaken to vindicate the Church of <hi>England</hi> from. And it is high time to doe it, for on that account they begin to look very ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon us, and eſteem us no better than Heathens and Publicans. And we are roundly told, that whilſt our Schiſm ſubſiſts uncleared, it is to no purpoſe to enter into debate with us about any particular points of Doctrine, nor are we to be hearkned to in any particular Controverſie. But if a bare accuſation without proof be a ſufficient Conviction, they may doe well to look to themſelves; for there are thoſe who will not ſtick to charge them with the ſame Crime, and perhaps upon better grounds than they charge us; and if ſo, then their Argument may be retorted upon themſelves. But I do not think a bare Re-crimination ſufficient either to clear
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152538:4"/>us, or burthen them, and therefore I have choſen another me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <hi>viz.</hi> by laying open the Nature of Schiſm, and ſtating the Notion of it in ſo large, plain and comprehenſive terms, that it may eaſily be applyed to thoſe who are guilty of it. And in purſuance of this method, I ſhall now preſent you with a Definition of Schiſm.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Definition of Schiſm. <hi>Schiſm is a voluntary and cauſeleſs Separation from the Communion of a Chriſtian Church of which we are Members.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>This I take to be as large and comprehenſive a Definition of Schiſm as they can juſtly require. By this we are willing to be tryed, and if found guilty, to ſubmit to the Cenſure due to Schiſmaticks; and would willingly hope (though as yet we have no great reaſon for it) that our Adverſaries will be ſo ingenuous too.</p>
                        <p>To put the matter therefore upon trial, I ſhall take this Definition in pieces, and having laid the ſeveral parts before you proceed to diſcourſe of them ſeverally.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Schiſm is a Separation, <hi>i. e.</hi> a breach of Unity, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of ſome well compacted Body.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. It is a Separation from a Chriſtian Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> from ſuch a Society between which and us, there either is or ought to be a Religious Union and Conjunction; for between <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Turks,</hi> there can be no Schiſm, becauſe they are not joyned together in any Religious Society.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. It is a Separation from the Communion of that Church, in Faith, Worſhip and Government, under that Notion, as they are bonds of Communion.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. It is a voluntary and cauſeleſs Separation, <hi>i. e.</hi> being neither forced thereunto, nor having any ſufficient cauſe or ground for ſo doing.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. It is a Separation from that Church of which we are Members, <hi>i. e.</hi> which hath a juriſdiction over us, and to which we owe ſubjection and obedience.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152538:5"/>
                     <head>SECT. III. I. <hi>Schiſm is a Separation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE word Schiſm naturally imports a Separation, and the word Separation, as naturally implies a breach of Unity, in which conſiſts a good part of the Nature of Schiſm. Yet are they not terms convertible, for though every Schiſm be a Separation, yet every Separation is not a Schiſm, in the ſtrict notion of it, unleſs it be attended with all thoſe other requiſites of a Schiſm. There may be a good and lawfull, as well as an evil and ſinfull Separation; if a Separation be grounded upon good reaſon, and managed to good ends and purpoſes, then is it not only good and lawfull, nor only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, but very well juſtifiable too. But if there be no good ground for it, nor any good end promoted by it, then is it evil and unlawfull, and by no means excuſable, much leſs juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable. The former of theſe ſeems to be warranted by the expreſs Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who tells us, <hi>That there can be no fellowſhip between righteouſneſs and unrighteouſneſs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
                        <hi>nor any Communion between light and darkneſs, nor any concord between Chriſt and Belial, nor any participation between a believer and an infidel, nor any agreement between the Temple of God and Idols.</hi> And thence concludes, <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean things, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you.</hi> And the other ſeems to be as plainly condemned by the ſame Apoſtle, who commands us <hi>to keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi> Eph. 4.3.</p>
                     <p>This may be farther illuſtrated by ſome familiar inſtances. Suppoſe a Society of Thieves and Robbers, or any other ſort of wicked men, united and linked together by ſome common ties, rules and laws, framed and deviſed by themſelves, for the ſupport of their wicked Community; if any one ſhould ſeparate himſelf from that Company, and thereby not only break the Unity, but do what in him lies to diſſolve the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf; would this be imputed to him as a Crime? Or would it not rather be looked upon by all mankind as a good and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152538:5"/>and in a ſober ſenſe as a meritorious Act? Or ſuppoſe any particular Society of Men, though legally eſtabliſhed, yet making the terms of their Communion ſuch, as could not in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and juſtice be complied with; if any one ſhould ſeparate himſelf from that Society, would it be a Crime in him: Or ought he not rather to be commended for it? But it is far otherwiſe in the Body Politique, which is the aggregation of all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, and all particular lawfull Societies; If any one ſhall ſeparate himſelf therefrom, and thereby break the Unity, and diſturb the Peace thereof; he will by all Men be judged guilty of Sedition and Treaſon: And the reaſon is evident, becauſe in the two former Caſes men have a greater liberty of judging and acting, than they have in this. For thoſe at beſt are but the Ordinances of Men, but Government is the Ordinance of God; and therefore though upon juſt ground we may ſeparate from them, though it be to the hazard of their Peace and Unity; yet can we have no juſt ground of Separation from this. For though the Governours may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times happen to be wicked and ungodly Men, yet the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtill is ſacred, and it is not for Subjects to call their Sovereigns to account; It is our duty to ſtudy and pray for the peace and ſafety, and to acquieſce in the rules and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations thereof; chuſing rather to ſuffer under it, than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Peace of it; And if either through the ignorance or inadvertency of thoſe in Authority there happen any Male-adminiſtration in the Government, it is not the governed but the Governours, that ſtand accountable to God for it.</p>
                     <p>And thus it is in the Church: Let us ſuppoſe a number of Schiſmaticks and Hereticks who have banded themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and formed themſelves into a Society under the ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Rules and Laws they could deviſe, as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Novatians</hi> of old did. If any one ſhould ſeparate himſelf from their Communion and return into the boſome of the Church; This certainly would never be imputed to him as a Crime. Or ſuppoſe a particular Church, though lawfully conſtituted, and eſtabliſhed under lawfull Governours, ſhould make the terms of her Communion ſuch, as that her Neighbour Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches could not without ſin and danger hold Communion with her; would a Separation in this caſe be adjudged a Schiſm? Or would it not rather be look'd upon as their duty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152538:6"/>to withdraw from her? But it is far otherwiſe in the One, Holy, Catholick and Apoſtolick Church; for though there may be ſome reaſons to warrant a Separation from thoſe; yet can there be no reaſon why we ſhould ſeparate from Her. And the reaſon is evident, becauſe ſhe being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God, and having his promiſe for her preſervation, can never give any occaſion thereof. Whoſoever therefore ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth from Her, puts himſelf out of the ordinary ways and means of Salvation, and becomes guilty of the greateſt and moſt dangerous Schiſm.</p>
                     <p>By this time, I hope, 'tis evident, that though every Schiſm import a Separation, yet every Separation doth not make a Schiſm. Nor is it every Unity that we are to be ſo tender of, but onely the Catholick Unity of God's Church. And now let us apply this to our preſent Caſe.</p>
                     <p>We are charged with Schiſm by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ſeparated from her Communion. Though this might ſafely be denied, and it might perhaps upon better grounds be ſaid, that ſhe hath ſeparated from us, not we from Her; yet for the preſent we'll admit of it, and give her this reaſon for it; We have ſeparated from Her, becauſe ſhe hath made the terms of her Communion ſuch, as, till they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, we cannot without ſin and danger joyn with Her.</p>
                     <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> being only a particular Church (and not the Catholick Church, as ſome of her Paraſites would fain perſuade us) hath no more ſecurity from Errour and Miſtakes than the reſt of Her Neighbours. And therefore if this reaſon be true, ſhe cannot deny (if ſhe will be ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) but that we have a juſt ground of Separation; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently are no Schiſmaticks. And that it is true, as it hath often been demonſtrated, ſo we are ready ſtill to doe the ſame again, whenever we ſhall be called to it. But that being no part of my deſign at this time, I ſhall proceed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152538:6"/>
                     <head>SECT. IV. II. <hi>Schiſm is a Separation from a Chriſtian Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS Separation is the Act, ſo a Chriſtian Church is the Subject of Schiſm, <hi>i. e.</hi> As it is a body compacted and united together by the Bands and Ligaments of our common Chriſtianity. For where there is no Union or Conjunction, there can be no Schiſm; And therefore between Chriſtians and Jews or Mahometans there can be no Schiſm; becauſe they are not joyned together in any Religious Society. Now the Chriſtian Church may be conſidered either as it is Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or Univerſal, or as it is Particular.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. If we conſider it as Catholick and Univerſal, there are three ſeveral Notions of it. Sometimes it is taken for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church diffuſive, <hi>i. e.</hi> for the whole body of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans diſperſed upon the face of the whole Earth; and ſo it comprehends all Perſons, and all particular Churches profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtianity. And this I take to be the true and genuine notion of the one holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Church, mentioned in our Creed. And whoſoever ſhall make a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or Separation from this Church, will be found guilty of a manifeſt, dangerous, and moſt abominable Schiſm. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is taken for the Catholick Church Repreſentative, <hi>i. e.</hi> for the Prelates and Paſtors of the Univerſal Church, delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their ſeveral particular Churches, and Aſſembled in a Counſel truly free and general. And whereever we meet with ſuch an one, we pay all deference and regard that is due to the Deciſions and Determinations of it And if any Man, or any Society of Men ſhall ſet up his or their private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt the publick Judgment of the Church, declared in a Council truly free and general, and ſhall be ſo tenacious of their own opinions, as upon that account to break Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church, I do not ſee, how they can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed from the ſin of Schiſm. Sometimes it is taken for the Catholick Church virtual, and ſo it is generally underſtood by our Adverſaries, though they do not agree among themſelves. For ſome of them would confine the notion of the Church vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152538:7"/>to the Pope alone, others to the Pope in Conclave; ſome to the Pope in Council, but theſe differ among themſelves, ſome telling us that the Pope is above the Council, others that the Council is above the Pope: others there are, who, to put a better Face upon the matter, do, by the Catholick Church virtual, underſtand the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all thoſe other Churches which are in Communion with Her. I ſhall not undertake to arbitrate this difference, but leaving theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parties to compromiſe the matter among themſelves, as well as they can: I ſhall call in an unexceptionable Witneſs to teſtifie that this is the notion which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> now hath of the Catholick Church, and that is <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi> the late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> who in his expoſition of the Catholick Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tells us he will ſay nothing, but what ſhall be warranted by the Church, and to make his words good, he produceth great Credentials from the Pope, and many other great Men. This great and learned Prelate in his Expoſition of the Catholick Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath theſe words. <hi>We acknowledge a Head eſtabliſhed by God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. 21. p. 50.</note> 
                        <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct his whole Flock in his paths, which Head is the Pope, as Succeſſour to St.</hi> Peter, <hi>the Prince of the Apoſtles, and that the Papal Chair is the common Centre of all Catholick Unity.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. 1. p. 2.</note> And in another place, he promiſeth not to meddle with any thing but the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> becauſe in them the Church hath given her deciſion upon theſe matters now in Agitation. Which Council was called by the Pope's Authority only, and the true ſenſe of all its Decrees, (by the Bull of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV.) reſerved to be explained by him alone. So that the great noiſe of the Catholick Church is at laſt dwindled into the Roman Catholick, which we of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> take to be a contradiction in <hi>Terminis,</hi> the ſame with a particular Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal; for they may as well ſay that the City of <hi>Rome</hi> is all the World, as that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Catholick Church. Beſides this notion of the Catholick Church virtual is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new, having no foundation either in the Holy Scriptures, or in any Primitive and Authentick Antiquity, and therefore we can by no means admit of it.</p>
                     <p>This is that Church by which, and towards which we are charged with the guilt of the horrible ſin of Schiſm. And God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152538:7"/>be thanked it is no worſe, for from any Criminal Schiſm in this caſe, I hope we ſhall, without any great difficulty, be able to acquit our ſelves.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If we conſider a Chriſtian Church as it is particular, then are we to underſtand it of a number of Men profeſſing Chriſtianity, formed into a Society under lawfull Governours, and governed by ſuch Laws and Rules, as are not different from, but agreeable to the Laws and Rules of the Catholick Church. And if any Man, or number of Men, who are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Society, ſhall without juſt cauſe ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Communion thereof; he or they ſo doing are certainly guilty of Schiſm. Nor is every occaſion which a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricious humour or diſcontent may ſuggeſt to us, to be taken as a ſufficient ground of Separation; Nay, though there be ſomething really amiſs, or at leaſt we are perſuaded that there is ſo, in the Doctrine, or Diſcipline of that Church whereof we are Members; yet ought we rather to ſuſpect our own Judgments, and ſuppreſs our own Sentiments, than break the unity and peace thereof. In a word, unleſs ſuch a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church ſhall make the terms of her Communion ſuch as cannot be complied with without ſin, I do not know any other juſt ground of Separation therefrom.</p>
                     <p>Thus have I conſidered the ſubject of Schiſm in its greateſt latitude. And now let us ſee how far any thing that may be gathered from hence can affect the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. If the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath made no defection from the Catholick Church diffuſive, <hi>i. e.</hi> from the <hi>One Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and Apoſtolick Church,</hi> which compriſeth all Men and all Societies of Men profeſſing Chriſtianity; Nor from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church repreſentative, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Prelates and Paſtours of the Univerſal Church lawfully aſſembled in a Council that is truly free and general. If ſhe profeſs no other Doctrine, nor exerciſe any other Diſcipline, than what ſhe hath received from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and was conſtantly profeſt and exerciſed by their Succeſſours in the primitive Church. If ſhe be willing to ſubmit all matters in difference between Her and any other Siſter-Church to be tried by the Holy Scriptures, the primitive Fathers, and the Deciſions of the four firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils. Then can ſhe not be juſtly charged with Schiſm upon that account. And that ſhe doth and is willing to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152538:8"/>doe all this that is here ſuppoſed, we are ready to make good, whenever our Adverſaries ſhall give us the occaſion ſo to doe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If their notion of a Church virtually Catholick be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether new, without any foundation either in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or in any primitive and authentick Antiquity; then the power and privileges which the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> challengeth upon that account are mere nullities, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Schiſm which ſhe chargeth of the Church <hi>England</hi> with upon that ſcore, a mere <hi>Chimera,</hi> which vaniſheth of it ſelf. If they think to avoid the force of this ſuppoſition, they muſt produce ſome good and authentick Record, which as yet hath not been diſcovered.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be onely a particular Church, and no otherwiſe Catholick than her Neighbours are, who profeſs the ſame common Chriſtianity. If ſhe can have no more power to cenſure us, than we have to cenſure Her, then can ſhe not without great preſumption, and great inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, charge us with the ſin of Schiſm. 'Tis true indeed we do not joyn in Communion with her, and the reaſon why we do not, I have given in the third Section. But it is as true, that we hold the Catholick Unity, and for the ſake of that, they themſelves will grant, that we may lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Unity of any particular Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. V. III. <hi>Schiſm is a Separation from the Communion of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS the Act of Schiſm is Separation, and the Subject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of a Chriſtian Church; ſo the Object in and about which the Separation is made, is the Communion of that Church. Now there are three great Bonds of Communion, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith, Worſhip and Government; and whoſoever ſhall ſeparate either from the Catholick or any particular Church whereof he is a Member in any of theſe, I do not ſee how he or they ſo doing can be acquitted from the guilt of Schiſm, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the corruption in ſome one or more of theſe be ſo great as to render the Communion ſinfull to him who knows it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152538:8"/>
                     <head>SECT. VI. I. <hi>Of Faith as it is a Bond of Communion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BY Faith here I underſtand the eſtabliſhed Doctrine of the Church, that common Chriſtianity which we all profeſs to own and embrace. For it is not every Doctrine that is received and taught in any particular Church, that is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Bond of Communion, but ſuch Doctrine as is or ought to be received by all. It is plain, and our Adverſaries them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will acknowledge it, that we may and ought to differ from particular Churches in ſome Doctrines; Otherwiſe why do they differ from us, from the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, and indeed all other Churches beſides their own in many things? On this ſcore is it, that we cannot receive their new Articles of Faith, thoſe additions which are made unto, and thoſe alterations which are made in the old and common Chriſtianity, by their Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We believe all that is contained in the Holy Scriptures to be infallibly true, all that was ever taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and their Succeſſours the Primitive Paſtours and Governours of the Church, we readily comply with; We believe all the Articles contained in thoſe three ancient Creeds, <hi>viz.</hi> that commonly called the Apoſtles, the <hi>Nicene,</hi> and the <hi>Athanaſian.</hi> We are willing to ſubmit to all the Deciſions and the Determinations of the four firſt General Councils, and to any Council that is lawfully called, and truly free and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. We are ready to receive all Traditions that are truly Apoſtolical, and we are willing to embrace any other truth as yet unknown to us, whenſoever or by whomſoever it ſhall be duly made out to be ſo And whilſt we this doe, we cannot truly be charged to have broken Communion with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, nor juſtly reputed Schiſmaticks therefrom.</p>
                     <p>And as for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe being only a particular Church, hath no juriſdiction at all over the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and conſequently no more power to cenſure us, than we have to cenſure her; for in this caſe the rule holds, <hi>(Par in parem non habet imperium)</hi> Equals have no Authority over
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152538:9"/>one another. And therefore for her to impoſe her new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and becauſe ſhe refuſeth to receive them, and joyn Communion with her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe terms, preſently cry out Schiſm, Schiſm, is ſo idle, ſo vain, ſo unaccountable a Clamour, as I am perſwaded the Learned among them cannot but diſapprove it. For whilſt we hold the Catholick Faith entire, and maintain Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the One Holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Church therein; though we differ from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other particular Church in ſome Doctrines; Yet is it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that we ſhould be guilty of a Schiſmatical Separation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from her or them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VII. II. <hi>Of Worſhip as it is a Bond of Communion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BY Worſhip here, I mean Publick Worſhip, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered only in its Subſtantials and Eſſentials, not as it is clothed with particular Modes, Rites and Ceremonies. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it can be no Bond of Communion. The ſubſtantial and eſſential Parts of Publick Worſhip, I take to be theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayer, reading the Holy Canon, interpreting the ſame, and the adminiſtration of the bleſſed Sacraments. Now theſe in divers Churches may be performed in different Manners, and with different Rites and Ceremonies, and yet thoſe Churches, notwithſtanding this, may ſtill hold Communion with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and conſequently be guilty of no Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Separation therefrom, nor from one another. But if we by Worſhip underſtand the eſtabliſhed Publick Worſhip of a particular Church, then are we to conſider it not as abſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from, but clothed with ſuch Modes, Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies as are thought convenient by that Church. And if any one who is a Member of ſuch a Church ſhall, upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended offence taken againſt any ſuch Modes, Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, ſeparate himſelf from the Publick Worſhip, I do not ſee how he can be acquitted from the guilt of Schiſm.</p>
                     <p>And this I take to be the caſe not only of the Proteſtant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152538:9"/>Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as they call themſelves) but of <hi>Engliſh Roman</hi> Catholicks too. For that they did hold actual Communion with us many years together in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, and neither then, nor ever ſince did pretend to take any offence at the Subſtantials of our Worſhip, is very plain and evident. And that it was not we that ſeparated from them, but they that ſeparated from us, is as manifeſt; and therefore it will concern them more than us, to clear themſelves from the ſin of Schiſm. And for this I know no other Plea they can make uſe of, than their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Univerſal Paſtour of God's Church, which Plea is to be conſidered under the next great Bond of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> Government.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VIII. III. <hi>Of Government as it is a Bond of Communion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THat our great and Univerſal Paſtour, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, did found and conſtitute a Church, and that he did not leave it without Laws and Rules to be governed by, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proper Governours inveſted with Power and Authority to exert and execute thoſe Laws we ſtedfaſtly believe. But that he ever did delegate all his Power to any <hi>One,</hi> or ſubſtitute any <hi>One</hi> Perſon to be the Univerſal Paſtour of the Church after him, we cannot believe, becauſe we have no ground for it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Scripture, or in any primitive and authentick Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And indeed how ſhould we? for till the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> began to envy one another's Greatneſs, and to ſtrive for Supremacy, (which was about 600 years after <hi>Chriſt</hi>) the Church was never acquainted with any ſuch name or thing, as is now claimed. And no ſooner did it adventure to peep abroad, but warning was given againſt it as Antichriſtian, and that by one of their Popes. And when afterwards it was publickly uſurped, it was condemned by a General Council; and they are not yet agreed among themſelves where to fix it. And therefore they cannot in reaſon expect that we ſhould build our Faith upon ſuch an uncertain Foundation, or make that a Bond of Communion in the Church, which the Church from 600 years and upwards knew nothing of.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152538:10"/>
                     <p>That Government is a Bond of Communion in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, we acknowledge; and that it was never lodged in the hands of any one Perſon ſince our Saviour, I think is very plain and evident. But where then doth it reſide? This will beſt be known, by conſidering how it is derived. That it was united in the Perſon of our Bleſſed Saviour, will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged on all hands; and where he left it, there we are to look for it Now that he left it with his Apoſtles, and made them equal ſharers therein, I think is very plain; (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that pretence which is made by our Adverſaries, that it was lodged in <hi>Peter</hi> alone; a pretence which hath been ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſo miſerably baffled, and which if it were true would doe them no ſervice, that I wonder they are not aſhamed to bring it upon the ſtage any more.) And that from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles it was derived to their Succeſſours, the Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours of God's Church, is the received opinion of all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſcopatus unus eſt, cujus à ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis in ſolidum pars tenetur.</hi> Cypr. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Eccleſiae Edit.</hi> Oxon. <hi>p.</hi> 108.</note> And that it now lies diſperſed among all the Paſtours and Biſhops of particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, (unleſs they be lawfully called and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Synods or Councils) under the Power, Protection and Aſſiſtance of Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, we verily believe. This is the notion we have of the viſible and external Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Catholick Church, and as it hath been, ſo if there were occaſion for it, may it ſtill be made appear to have been the very notion, that all the World (except thoſe who have ſubmitted to the Uſurpation of <hi>Rome)</hi> ever had, and ſtill have of it to this day. Now the Laws and Rules by which this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is adminiſtred, are to be found in the Holy Scriptures, in the Uſages and Cuſtoms of the Primitive Church, and in the Canons and Conſtitutions of the four firſt General Councils.</p>
                     <p>But if by Government, we underſtand the Government of particular Churches, then is it lodged in the Paſtours and Governours of thoſe Churches, and is to be adminiſtred by them according to ſuch Laws and Rules as are agreeable to thoſe of the Catholick Church. And in this caſe, it can have no influence from one National Church to another; for, as ſuch, they are equal; and Equals have no power over one another. But whoſoever is a Member of any ſuch Church, and refuſeth all due obedience to the Paſtours and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours thereof, doth thereby contract the guilt of Schiſm.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152538:10"/>
                     <p>Now whether the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the violation of all theſe Bonds of Communion, have diſturbed the Peace of the Chriſtian Church, broken the Unity of the Univerſal, and of all particular Churches, and thereby incurred the guilt of Schiſm; you may take a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in this ſhort parallel which I ſhall now lay before you.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. As for Faith conſidered as a Bond of Communion. What the Church of <hi>England</hi> believes, and what ſhe is ready and willing to comply with, I have told you in the 6th Sect. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> not contented therewith, added to the ſacred Canon ſome Apocryphal Books, which were never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received either into the Jewiſh or Chriſtian Canon. And as if the revealed Will of God were an imperfect Rule, ſhe undertakes to ſupply the defects of it, by groundleſs Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. She makes new Creeds (witneſs the <hi>Trent</hi> Creed) and that both without the conſent of the preſent, and againſt the Doctrine and Practice of ancient Churches. Now which of theſe hath violated this Bond of Communion, Judge ye.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. As for Worſhip conſidered as a Bond of Communion, I have given you our Sentiments of it, and told you wherein it conſiſts in the 7th. Sect. Now how far the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath corrupted that pure Worſhip of God, both by her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions and additions, I ſhall briefly acquaint you. As for Prayer it muſt be performed in publick in an unknown tongue, which the People underſtand not. So that they muſt not know what they pray for, and conſequently cannot with any true devotion ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi> It muſt be offered to Saints and Angels, and not immediately to God, who glories to be ſtyled a God hearing Prayers: and this we take to be an Act of Religious Worſhip due to the Creatour only, but by them paid to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. As for the reading of Holy Scriptures, if any portion of them be read in publick, it muſt be in <hi>Latin,</hi> a Language not underſtood by the People, and therefore impoſſible for them to be inſtructed by it. It is true indeed they ſometimes interpret ſome portion of Scripture, by preaching in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar language; but then the People muſt take all they ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt, they muſt not without ſpecial leave be allowed the Bible in their own Language, no not in private, leſt with the Noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> they ſhould examine whether thoſe things be ſo or no. As for the Sacraments, they have added five that were never inſtituted by Chriſt, and taken away half of one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152538:11"/>of thoſe, which they cannot but own was of his Inſtitution; <hi>i. e.</hi> they deprive the Laity of the Cup in the Lord's Supper; beſides thoſe many Superſtitions which they have intermix'd, and therewith corrupted the pure and primitive Worſhip of God. Now let any indifferent Perſon judge, whether they or we have violated this Bond of Communion, and conſequently which of us may be charged with Schiſm.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 As for Government conſidered as a Bond of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What our thoughts are of it, you may ſee in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Sect. Now how far the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, not only from us, but from the Catholick Church both ancient and modern, and from all other particular Churches in this point, will appear, if we conſider: That ſhe uſurps a Dominion condemned as Antichriſtian by one of their own Popes, diſowned by the whole Church at that time, and which we at preſent cannot own without betraying the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church. That by virtue of this Uſurped Power ſhe impoſeth unreaſonable and unlawfull conditions of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for non-compliance therewith excommunicates not only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but, as ſome will tell you, three parts of the Chriſtian World beſides. Now if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by ſetting up and exerciſing this Exorbitant Power, hath broken this Bond of Communion, then who is chargeable with the Schiſm, judge ye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. IX. IV. <hi>Schiſm is a voluntary and cauſeleſs Separation from the Communion of a Chriſtian Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THeſe are the two conditions of Schiſm, it muſt be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and cauſeleſs; and from theſe two conditions it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives its greateſt aggravation, and becomes a ſin of the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt dye and greateſt guilt.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>It muſt be a Voluntary Separation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I call it Voluntary, to diſtinguiſh ſin from puniſhment, Schiſm from excommunication; for though by the latter a man be caſt out of the Church, and made no member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yet ſtrictly ſpeaking, he is thereby ſeparated from the Church, and doth not ſeparate himſelf. 'Tis true that every
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152538:11"/>ſin is a voluntary act in the ſinner, but doth that excuſe him? or rather doth it not aggravate his guilt? If a man be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the communion of the Church by ſome preſſing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, this may be his misfortune and not his fault: Or if a man be under a conſtraint, and have a force put upon him: if he be frighted with threats and menaces, or wheadled with promiſes and allurements; if his fears and hopes, thoſe two prevalent paſſions in man, be raiſed to that height, as to darken his underſtanding, and overpower his will; theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances may extenuate though they cannot altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his guilt. But when a man doeth an evil action not by chance, but of choice; not by force, but by inclination; not raſhly and inconſiderately, but deliberately and adviſedly; this makes his ſin to be exceeding ſinfull. For thereby the Schiſmatick puts himſelf out of the ordinary way and means of ſalvation, divideth the body of Chriſt, deſpiſeth and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Church of God, and breaketh the bond of peace, which ought to be kept intire and inviolate. And therefore do I make this a Condition of Schiſm, becauſe if we can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Separation from the communion of the Church to be involuntary, it will not deſerve that name.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. X. II. <hi>It muſt be a Cauſeleſs Separation,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>THAT Schiſm in it ſelf is a great and grievous ſin, and in its conſequences extremely miſchievous to the Church of God, and to the Schiſmatick himſelf, is agreed on all hands. But how much greater muſt the ſin needs be when thereby all this guilt is contracted, and all this miſchief done without any cauſe. <hi>i. e.</hi> without any ſufficient cauſe.</p>
                     <p>Now a Separation may be conſidered either as it relates to the Catholick, or Particular Churches. And then a Separation from the Catholick Church taken in the moſt comprehenſive ſenſe, is not Schiſm but Apoſtaſie, and it will be impoſſible for any man to find a ſufficient reaſon for that.</p>
                     <p>But if it be conſidered as a ſeparation from the communion of ſome particular Church, then it is implied that poſſibly there may be ſuch cauſe given, as may juſtifie the Separation;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152538:12"/>and if ſo, then the guilt of Schiſm will lie at the door of that Church which gives ſuch cauſe, and not at his or theirs who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate therefrom. Now I have already told you, that I know no cauſe which can juſtifie ſuch a Separation, ſave onely this, when a Church makes the terms of her Communion ſuch as cannot be complied withall without ſin. And in this caſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it is very plain, That it cannot be ſin to ſeparate, when it is ſin to communicate; for no Laws of Men can abrogate or diſſolve the obligation of the expreſs Laws of God. But if there be no ſuch cauſe, then to break communion with any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, upon any other account, will amount to a Cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Separation, and conſequently incur the guilt of Schiſm.</p>
                     <p>If therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever did, or now doth forſake the communion of the <hi>One Holy Catholick and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church;</hi> or if ſhe ever did, or now doth voluntarily and cauſeleſly break communion with any particular Chriſtian Church, then may there be ſome colour to charge her with the ſin of Schiſm; but if none of all this can be made appear againſt her, then ought ſhe to be acquitted of that charge. Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuch thing can be made out againſt her, or whether the whole charge will not fall heavy upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> will appear in the ſequel of this Diſcourſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. XI. V. <hi>Schiſm is a Separation from the Communion of that Church of which we are Members.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis is the laſt part of our Definition, and I add theſe words (of which we are Members) becauſe Schiſm imports a Diviſion of ſome united and well compacted Body, or a making two of that which before was but one. On this ſcore is it, that we cannot charge <hi>Turks, Pagans</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> with Schiſm, becauſe they never were of the Chriſtian Church, nor joyned with her in any Religious Society. And here the Church will be at a great loſs how to fix the guilt of Schiſm upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for if we neither are nor ever of right ought to have been under the Government of that Church, then hath ſhe no Juriſdiction over us, nor do we owe her any ſubjection and obedience, and conſequently cannot be guilty of Schiſm to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152538:12"/>her, nor hath ſhe any power to cenſure us for it. We own her to be a Siſter-Church, and a true, though unſound Member of the Catholick Church, and ſo far as ſhe holds the Catholick Faith and Worſhip, we are ready and willing to hold Communion with her. But we cannot ſubmit to her Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, nor communicate with her in thoſe Errours, Abuſes, Superſtitions, Additions, Subtractions and Alterations, by which ſhe hath ſo groſly corrupted the pure and primitive Faith and Worſhip of God's Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. XII. <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>acquitted from the Scandal of Schiſm.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF this Definition of Schiſm be allowed, (as I ſee no cauſe, why they ſhould diſown it) and not applicable to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then is ſhe unjuſtly charged with the guilt of Schiſm by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now whether it be applicable to the Church of <hi>England</hi> will appear, by taking a review of the ſeveral parts of it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Schiſm is a Separation, <hi>i. e.</hi> a breach of Unity, or a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſome well compacted Body. And here we are charged for breaking the Unity, and dividing the Body of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church, as they call it. To which I anſwer, if that Church were truly Catholick either in reſpect of place or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, this charge would lie heavy upon us; but being neither, we ſhall be able with leſs difficulty to anſwer this Objection. It muſt be acknowledged that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> at the time of the Reformation, and ſome long time before that had uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a certain Power and Dominion over us; and had exerted the ſame in ſuch extravagant impoſitions as at laſt became too heavy for us to bear. That Church had indeed by a long cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome gained ſuch an aſcendent over our Fore fathers, that ſhe had enſlaved their Judgments, and obtruded what ſhe pleaſed upon them; ſhe had unawares led them into many Errours in Doctrine, many Superſtitions in Worſhip, and almoſt ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up their Liberty in Point of Government. At length it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to open the Eyes of our Fore-fathers, to ſee the ſlavery and bondage they were in, and how far they were gone from the Unity of the Catholick Church, both in Faith, in Worſhip,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152538:13"/>and in Government. To retrieve themſelves, many Efforts were made, and great Endeavours uſed for a Reformation. But none of thoſe prevailing, they at laſt bethought themſelves of caſting off the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke, which by the aſſiſtance of the Civil Authority, not in tumultuary, but in a regular way was effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and when that was done, then upon mature deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they reform thoſe other abuſes which were crept in among them. Whether this broke Catholick Unity or no, let the World judge.</p>
                     <p>If this be a Schiſm, we muſt own our ſelves guilty of it, but we ſee no reaſon to own it to be ſo yet, for in all this we have done nothing but what we are able to juſtifie before all the World. For even our Adverſaries themſelves will not deny, but that a National Church hath power in it ſelf to reform abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes within it ſelf. But it may be they will tell us, that we are not a Church, but a faction, or party made up of Schiſmaticks and Hereticks broke looſe from the Church. If this were true, we ſhould have little to ſay for our ſelves, but a bare accuſation is no proof. They may do well therefore to recollect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and conſider, that before <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk ſet his Foot in <hi>England,</hi> there was a Chriſtian Church ſettled here under lawfull Governours; which Church oppoſed the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of that proud Monk, and denyed obedience to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for which they ſeverely ſuffered. If notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, our Adverſaries ſhall, as they frequently do, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive that old thred-bare queſtion, ſo often baffled; Where was your Church before the Reformation? Our anſwer is ready, it was where it is, the ſame for ſubſtance now, that it was then; It is indeed reformed and repaired, but not made new; There is not one ſtone of a new foundation laid by us, the old Walls ſtand ſtill, only the overcaſting of thoſe ancient ſtones with the untempered Mortar of new inventions diſpleaſed us, and that we waſhed off.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Durand. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. l.</hi> 1.</note> What their own <hi>Durandus</hi> ſaith of material Churches, is very applicable to the Spiritual. If the wall be decayed not at once, but ſucceſſively; it is judged ſtill the ſame Church; and (upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration) not to be reconſecrated, but only reconciled. If therefore our Church be the ſame for ſubſtance now, that it was before the Reformation, then it is plain that by our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation we made no Separation from the Church; we only laid aſide the corruptions, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe unſound and unwholſome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152538:13"/>additions, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had made to the ancient Structure of Chriſt's Religion; and when thoſe were removed, the Church which was by them obſcured, appeared again in her primitive Luſtre and Beauty. Now if the Church be the ſame ſtill, it will neceſſarily follow, that we who are of that Church do now hold the ſame Communion in all the Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials and Eſſentials of Religion with all other Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that we did before. For as to all the Eſſentials of a Church we hold the ſame Faith, the ſame Worſhip, and the ſame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment now, that we did before the Reformation; and which now is, and always hath been owned by the Catholick. Church in all Ages. And if ſo, then can we not poſſibly be guilty of any Schiſmatical Separation.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Schiſm is a Separation from a Chriſtian Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> from ſuch a Society between which and us there is or ought to be a Religious Union and Conjunction. That we cannot upon that ſcore be juſtly charged with any Schiſmatical Separation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Catholick, or any particular Chriſtian Church, I hope is ſufficiently made out in the 4th. Sect. of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to which I refer the Reader, being unwilling either to give him or my ſelf an unneceſſary trouble.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Schiſm is a Separation from the Communion of a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Church, in Faith, Worſhip and Government, conſidered as Bonds of Communion. And here we are roundly charged by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with a Schiſmatical Separation from her, and a manifeſt breach of all theſe great Bonds of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. But having in the beginning of this Sect. I hope, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently vindicated the Church of <hi>England</hi> from any Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Separation from the Catholick or any other Chriſtian Church, in her Reformation; and cleared her innocency as to the breach of any of theſe great Bonds of Communion, in the 5th, 6th, 7th, and 8th, Sections, I ſhall not need to ſay any more of it here. There is only one thing which as yet I have taken no notice of, and with which they often twit us, <hi>viz.</hi> The Derivation of our Orders from them.</p>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Harding</hi> in his anſwer to Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi>'s Apology doth mightily triumph in this, telling us, That a Church cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without lawfull Paſtours and Governours, that there can be none ſuch without lawfull Ordination by impoſition of hands; that we neither have nor ever had any ſuch but from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that thoſe who received that power
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152538:14"/>from her, becoming Schiſmaticks and Hereticks by their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from her, forfeited that power, and could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey it to others; that therefore we have now no ſuch thing as lawfull Prieſts and Biſhops among us, without which we cannot be a Church; that herein we have broken the great Bond of Communion, <hi>viz.</hi> Government, by departing from that Church from which ours had its Being; and therefore cannot be excuſed from the ſin of Schiſm. To this B. <hi>Jewel</hi> hath given a long, learned and full anſwer, to which I ſhall refer the Reader. He may find it in the ſecond part of the defence of the Apology of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Chap. 5. Diviſion 1. But to ſhew you in how empty and inſignificant a ſhow this mighty triumph ends, I ſhall here offer ſome few things to conſideration</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the conferring of Orders giveth no Power or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to him or them by whom they are conferred, over him or them on whom they are conferred. For, do we not know, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is always conſecrated by the Biſhop of <hi>Hoſtia,</hi> and yet I hope they will not ſay that the Biſhop of <hi>Hoſtia</hi> is therefore above the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Let it be granted that we derive our Orders from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (not as from the Fountain or Original of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but as from the conduct or means of conveyance) I would ask this queſtion, do they believe their Orders to be good and valid, or not? If not, why do they preſume to exerciſe thoſe high and holy Functions to which they are admitted thereby? If they do, then our Orders muſt be good and valid too, and we have as good right as they have to that Succeſſion which they ſo much boaſt of.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the Biſhops and Paſtours of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are true and rightfull Succeſſours to thoſe that have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, being elected, conſecrated, confirmed and admitted in as an effectual a manner as they were. If their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours were deceived in any thing, they ſucceed them in Place, but not in Errour. For though they were indeed their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours in Office, yet were they not the Rulers and Standards of their Faith. And it cannot be denyed but that a Succeſſion in Faith and Doctrine, is far more conſiderable than a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Perſons, and that (God be thanked) we are able to make good from the pure and uncorrupted Fountain. In Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine therefore we ſucceed the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Day
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152538:14"/>ſucceedeth the Night, as the Light ſucceedeth Darkneſs, and as Truth ſucceedeth Errour.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That thoſe Biſhops and Paſtours who have once been duly elected, conſecrated, confirmed and admitted in and to thoſe ſacred Functions, do not by departing from the Errours and Superſtitions of any other Church, (though it be that from which they received their Orders) loſe the power that was thereby committed to them, but are ſtill in a capacity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the ſame unto others.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That the Biſhops and Paſtours of the Church of <hi>England</hi> being legally poſſeſſed of, having duly exerted, and conſtantly and regularly exerciſed this power; the Orders conferred by them by virtue thereof, are to all intents and purpoſes good and valid, and conſequently our Church cannot be ſaid to want true and lawfull Paſtours and Governours.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. That though the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in her Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, have caſt off the Uſurpations, and laid aſide the corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet hath ſhe not thereby broken any Bond of Communion with the Chriſtian Church; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot juſtly be charged with the guilt of Schiſm. For whilſt ſhe holds faſt thoſe three great Bonds of Communion, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith, Worſhip, and Government, in all the ſubſtantial and eſſential Parts thereof, the guilt of that horrid Schiſm, which hath ſo much bruiſed and wounded, rent and torn the Church of God, can never be laid at her door.</p>
                     <p>Theſe things I thought good to offer to conſideration, and when they are ſeriouſly and deliberately weighed, I do not doubt, but that the ingenuous Reader will ſo well improve them, as to ſatisfie himſelf and others, that all this mighty tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph is no more than a vain and empty ſhow.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Schiſm is a voluntary and cauſeleſs Separation from the Communion of a Chriſtian Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> When men have full liberty to make their own choice, having no force nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint put upon their inclinations; nor any cauſe or occaſion given to juſtifie their Separation; then may they be truly ſaid to act voluntarily and without cauſe. And if this be our caſe, we muſt confeſs our ſelves guilty of Schiſm, but if not, then are we unjuſtly charged with it.</p>
                     <p>That our receſſion from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was not a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary act in us, but a neceſſity upon us, occaſioned by force and violence, conſtraint and compulſion, is plain and evident.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152538:15"/>We did not attempt a Separation, but only deſire a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo we might walk together in the Houſe of God as friends; If they would have hearkned to us, and removed thoſe errours and abuſes, thoſe Superſtitions and corruptions, that tyranny and uſurpation, which they had introduced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Faith, Worſhip and Government of Chriſt's Church, we had ſtill peaceably continued in Communion with them. But ſo far were they from hearkning to theſe our juſt deſires, that inſtead thereof, we were menaced with fire and fagot, with impriſonment, with confiſcation of our Eſtates, with all kind of ſufferings, and even death it ſelf, if we refuſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with their Corruptions and innovations. And therefore we may truly ſay with the Learned <hi>Cauſaubon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cauſaub. ad Peron.</note> 
                        <hi>Non fugimus ſed fugamur,</hi> We did not run away from them, but were driven away by them.</p>
                     <p>But yet notwithſtanding all this force and violence, if we had not ſufficient cauſe to juſtifie our receſſion, we muſt ſtill be criminal;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Euſch. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 44.</note> for we are of opinion with <hi>Dionyſius Alex.</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Novatus,</hi> That any thing muſt rather be born, than that we ſhould rend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder the Church of God. But alas we had too great cauſe for what we did; The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had corrupted the Faith of God's Church with her unwarrantable additions and alterations; The primitive beauty and purity of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhe had defaced with Superſtitions: That goodly and well compacted ſtructure of Government which had been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and eſtabliſhed in the Church of God, ſhe had quite demoliſhed; and inſtead thereof had erected an unheard of tyrannical Government unknown to the Primitive Church, and condemned by all other Churches, ever ſince it appeared in the World. In a word, ſhe had made the terms of her Communion ſuch, as could not be complied with without ſin; and when it is ſin to communicate, it cannot be ſin to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate.</p>
                     <p>Thus much I hope may ſuffice, to ſatisfie any indifferent and unprejudic'd Reader, that the receſſion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from that of <hi>Rome</hi> in her Reformation, was neither owing to a dividing humour, nor without juſt cauſe. And therefore ſhe is unjuſtly charged with the guilt of Schiſm by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon that account.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Schiſm is a voluntary and cauſeleſs Separation from the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152538:15"/>Communion of a Chriſtian Church of which we are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>i. e.</hi> which hath a Juriſdiction over us, and to which we owe Subjection and Obedience. Schiſm imports a breach of Unity, a dividing of that Body which before was but one; it implies the caſting off of a lawfull Juriſdiction, to which we were obliged to yield Subjection and Obedience. Now if we neither are, nor ever were of right Subjects of that Church; if we neither are, nor ever were ſuch parts of that Body as are to depend upon the Head of it, then can we not juſtly be charged with breaking the Unity of that Church, or divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that Body, becauſe that Church, or that Body doth ſtill remain the ſame it was notwithſtanding our receſſion therefrom. And if it neither hath, nor ever had any lawfull Juriſdiction over us, then we neither do, nor ever did owe any ſubjection or obedience thereunto; and therefore cannot without great injuſtice be charged with a Schiſmatical Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefrom.</p>
                     <p>To prove this Negative, would require a much longer Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe than is now deſigned; and therefore at preſent I ſhall only ſay, that this we inſiſt upon. That the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> neither is, nor ever was by any divine Authority bound to be in obedience to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And whenever they pleaſe to make their claim, we are ready to defend our ſelves againſt it. In the mean time, till they make this good, they have no reaſon to brand us, (as hitherto they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly done) with the odious Names of Schiſmaticks and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
                     <p>Thus have I taken a review of the ſeveral parts of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, which (if it be allowed) will fairly acquit the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the guilt of Schiſm. And now let us ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can ſo well diſcharge her ſelf of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>guilty of that Shiſm, with which they charge the Church of</hi> England.</head>
                     <p>IT is a rule generally allowed, that the Cauſe makes the Schiſm. If the Church gives cauſe of Separation, there is the Schiſm; if not, the cauſe of Schiſm is in the Separatiſt. So
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152538:16"/>that where the cauſe is found, there the charge of Schiſm reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. If therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath given juſt cauſe of Separation from her, then is ſhe cauſally guilty of that Schiſm; and I am afraid will hardly be able to acquit her ſelf from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, of almoſt all other Schiſms in the Church.</p>
                     <p>Their ingenuous <hi>Caſſander</hi> confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">Caſſ. de Offic. boni viri, &amp;c.</note> that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is not a little changed from her ancient beauty and brightneſs, and that ſhe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with many diſeaſes, and vicious diſtempers. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſick,
<note place="margin">Bernh. de vita ſolit.</note> St. <hi>Bernhard</hi> undertakes to be her Phyſician, and preſcribes her a Diet, which he tells us muſt be profitable though unpleaſing; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhe ought to be reproved, and a Reformation required. And if thereupon an offence be taken,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Bernh. ad Hug. de Sancto vict. Epiſt.</hi> 77.</note> the ſame Saint <hi>Bernhard</hi> ſhall acquaint you where the ſcandal will reſt, When ſaults are taxed, and ſcandal grows thereupon. He is the cauſe of the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, who did that which was worthy to be reproved, not he that reproved the ill doer. And that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath given occaſion both to the reproof and ſcandal, let their own Preſident in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> inform you. Who ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Orat. praeſ. Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Seſſ.</hi> 11.</note> That <hi>the Depravation and Corruption of Diſcipline and Manners in the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>was in a great meaſure the Cauſe and Original of all thoſe Schiſms and Hereſies, which then troubled the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But that it may appear that I have a deſire to deal fairly and friendly with them, I ſhall here preſent them with a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py of their Charge, and give them time to plead to it. The Charge was long ſince drawn up by two great men of our Church, <hi>viz.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bramhal,</hi> and never yet pleaded to that I know, much leſs cleared.</p>
                     <p>Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in a little Book intituled <hi>The Old Religion,</hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to his Dioceſs of <hi>Exeter,</hi> chap. 4. lays down their Charge in theſe five particulars.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Nothing can be more plain, than that the</hi> Roman <hi>is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, as the Fathers of</hi> Baſil <hi>well diſtinguiſh it, not the Univerſal; though we take in the Churches of her ſubordination or correſpondence. This truth we might make good by authority, if our very ſenſes did not ſave us the labour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>No particular Church (to ſay nothing of the Univerſal ſince the Apoſtolick times) can have power to make a fundamental point
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152538:16"/>of Faith; It may explain or declare, it cannot create Articles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Onely an Errour againſt a point of Faith, is Hereſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Thoſe Points wherein we differ from</hi> Romaniſts <hi>are they, which only the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath made fundamental, and of Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>The Reformed, therefore being by that Church illegally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for thoſe Points, are not Hereticks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This I take to be a fair diſcharge for the Church of <hi>England</hi> from that foul aſperſion which hath been caſt upon her by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But Biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi> chargeth them more home, and particularly in five Articles more, and lays the ſin at their door.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>uſurps an higher place and power in the Body Eccleſiaſtical, than of right is due unto her.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Se ſeparateth, both by her Doctrines and Cenſures, three parts of the Chriſtian World from her Communion, and as much as in her lies, from the Communion of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>She rebelleth againſt general Councils.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>She breaks, or takes away all the lines of Apoſtolical Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion except her own; and appropriates all Original Juriſdiction to her ſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>She challenges a temporal power over Princes, either directly or indirectly; which draws Sedition and Rebellion after it, and is no ſmall aggravation of their Schiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe are the things we charge them with; if they can tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plead not guilty thereunto, then are we criminal; But if they cannot, if theſe things be really true, then are they cauſally guilty of that Schiſm with which they would charge us; and the whole weight with all the dreadfull conſequences thereof will lie at their doors, and be an heavy burthen upon them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>The Concluſion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THat there is, and for a long time hath been a great and grievous Schiſm in the Church, and that thoſe who have been guilty of it, have miſerably rent and torn, and even ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out the Bowels of their common Mother, What conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152538:17"/>Perſon can be ignorant? and who can know it without tears of pity, and prayers to God for the reſtoration of the Church's Peace and Unity? This would much better become us, than diſputing about it; and this, I declare, ſhould have been my Province, had not the daily and loud Clamours of the guilty Party ſo unjuſtly aſſaulted the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and forced me from my Privacy, to undertake this neceſſary and juſt Defence of my dear Mother.</p>
                     <p>It hath for a long time been matter of debate, and a ball of contention, where the cauſe of the Schiſm was to be ſound: The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with great confidence and aſſurance, hath laid it at the door of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and that Church upon better grounds, hath charged the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with it: I pray God open both their and our Eyes, that we may all ſee and know the things that belong unto our Peace; that laying aſide all rancour and animoſity, we may at laſt joyn hearts and hands to promote Truth and Holineſs, and ſtudy nothing more than to <hi>keep the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For my own part, I have ſo great an abhorrence for the ſin of Schiſm, that I do ſeriouſly profeſs, if I were convinced, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> were guilty of the Schiſm, I would rather chuſe to ſuffer any thing elſewhere, than conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in it; but, God be thanked, I am otherwiſe perſwaded, and ſo well ſatisfied therein, that as I have lived, ſo I hope I ſhall die in the Communion of that Church.</p>
                     <p>But alas! Perfect Peace and Unity are too great Bleſſings to be hoped for in this ſinfull World; they may be Objects of our Prayers, but hardly of our Hopes. However if we are what we pretend to be, <hi>i. e.</hi> humble and obedient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, it would well become us, in our ſeveral Stations, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Apoſtle's Rule, which bids us, <hi>Follow Peace with all Men, and Holineſs, without which no Man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12. <hi>v.</hi> 14. <hi>Now the God of Peace, who brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus, the great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Bloud of the Everlaſting Covenant, make us all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all good Works, to doe his Will, working in us that which is pleaſant in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe for ever and ever.</hi> Amen. Heb. 13. <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152538:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Church of England</hi> From the foul Aſperſions of Schiſm and Hereſie Unjuſtly caſt upon Her by <hi>The Church of Rome.</hi> PART. II.</p>
                  <q>—<hi>After the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers, believing all things which are written in the Law and the Prophets.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Acts 24.14.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Luke Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152538:18"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152538:18"/>
                  <head>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <div type="introduction">
                     <head>The INTRODUCTION.</head>
                     <p>HEreſie is a crime of ſo crimſon a dye, ſo heinous in it ſelf, and of ſo dangerous and deſtructive conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence both to the Heretick himſelf, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that, without great, plain and pregnant proof, to charge any Chriſtian, or Society of Chriſtians therewith, doth evidently betray a raſh, cenſorious, malicious and unchriſtian temper in them that doe it. I cannot but wonder therefore that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon ſo light and inſufficient grounds, ſhould be ſo liberal in beſtowing this Character upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe of her Communion.
<note place="margin">De corrupt artib.</note> 
                        <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> one of their own Men did long ſince complain of this, ſaying, <hi>Haereſis nomen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus leviſſimis impingitur, &amp;c.</hi> The name of Hereſie is laid upon every light matter; ſo would the <hi>Scotiſts</hi> deal with the <hi>Thomiſts,</hi> if the cuſtome of the Schools had not made the name ſo familiar. It is a good caution, and worthy to be attended to, which <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Haereſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 79.</note> another of their own Doctors, gives in this caſe, <hi>Idcirco fit, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore it happeneth that they who ſo raſhly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152538:19"/>pronounce and call every thing Hereſie, not conſidering what or whereof they ſpeak, are often ſmitten with their own dart, and fall into the ſame pit which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had digged for others. For this I ſhould rather call Hereſie, to advance the Writings of Men unto the ſame degree of honour with the Word of God; which they do, who think it altogether as impious to diſſent from them, as from the Scriptures of God.</p>
                     <p>We freely confeſs, with St. <hi>Auſtin, Errare poſſumus,</hi> We may miſtake and be in an errour; but we as fully reſolve, with that holy Father, <hi>Haeretici eſſe nolumus,</hi> We will never be guilty of Hereſie. We have too great an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence for it, and are too well acquainted with the miſchief of it, to run our ſelves upon that rock. We are well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied how dangerous and deſtructive Hereſie is. It with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws men from the way of Truth, and makes them ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and blaſphemers of it:
<note place="margin">Gal 5.20, 21.</note> 
                        <hi>It excludes men from the Kingdom of God, and makes them become men of corrupt minds,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> and reprobate concerning the Faith. Nor is it only hurtfull to thoſe that are guilty of it, but to others alſo. For, It doth grievouſly diſturb and trouble the peace of God's Church, by ſtirring up ſtrife, contention, emulation and diviſion among the members thereof. It ſeduceth unwary Souls, and betrays them to their own ruine and deſtruction. It weakens the authority of Holy Scriptures, and deprives men of the profit and advantage thereof, by perverting ſometimes the ſenſe, and ſometimes the letter of thoſe Sacred Writings. In a word, it makes the Chriſtian Religion to be evil ſpoken of among thoſe who are without.</p>
                     <p>Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> gives us a ſhort but full deſcription of it,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Defenſ. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. &amp;c.</hi> part. 1. chap. 7. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 43.</note> when he tells us, <hi>Hereſie is a forſaking of ſalvation, a renouncing of God's grace, a departing from the body and ſpirit of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe are our Sentiments of the ſin of Hereſie, and if our Adverſaries can draw a Character more black, we ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152538:19"/>promiſe, and ſeriouſly declare, that, ſo far as it is true, we are ready to joyn with them. And after all this can any one ſuſpect that we ſhould be in love with Hereſie?</p>
                     <p>But whether we be or no, it matters not, ſo long as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which thinks her ſelf infallible, is pleaſed to charge us therewith, to fix that title upon us, and as ſuch to repreſent us to the World. How juſtly, or unjuſtly rather this foul aſperſion is caſt upon us, will be enquired into in the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the deſign of the Authour therein being, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Church of <hi>England</hi> therefrom, which if he ſhall be ſo happy as to doe, then will it appear that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was mightily miſtaken in her Cenſure, and that will be no ſmall flaw in her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility; but if upon a fair and full debate it ſhall plainly appear, that they who ſo raſhly pronounce and call us Hereticks, be themſelves the guilty perſons, then will it highly concern them (if they have any care of their Souls) to conſider how deeply they are wounded with their own dart; and how low they are fallen into that Pit which they had digged for us; that ſo by a true and timely repentance they may riſe again.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152538:20"/>
                     <head>SECT. I. <hi>Of Hereſie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IN order to a right ſtating of the true and genuine Notion of Hereſie; it will be requiſite to conſider both the Importance of the Name, and the Nature of the Thing.</p>
                     <p>The word Hereſie is a Greek word,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <hi>ab</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>vel</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> and admits of many, and thoſe different ſignifications, as <hi>Scapula</hi> informs us out of ſeveral Authours. To reckon them all up, would waſt too much time and paper, and conduce but little to the deſign in hand; I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore onely mention three.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. I find it ſometimes rendered, conquering or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing, thus it is uſed by <hi>Herodot.</hi> and <hi>Thucyd.</hi> in whom we meet with theſe expreſſions. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to ſubdue a City,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Epit.</hi> Baſilii.</note> and thus it is uſed by <hi>Greg. Naz.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Thou ſhalt not overcome us.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It is ſometimes rendered Election or Option, as appears by theſe expreſſions, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to make choice of friends, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, I chooſe my way, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to chooſe a Judge, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, erring in the very choice of things, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the Election or Creation of an Emperour.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Epiſt. ad</hi> Galat.</note> And thus St. <hi>Hier.</hi> uſeth it, where he ſaith, Hereſie, in Greek, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which ſignifies Election, becauſe every one chooſeth to himſelf that diſcipline which he thinks beſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Sometimes it denotes a Sect or ſort of men, who having eſpouſed an opinion different from the received
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152538:20"/>opinion of all others, do tenaciouſly hold the ſame. Thus is the word uſually taken by Philoſophers, and Divines; <hi>Galen</hi> meeting with ſome of his own profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who both in their opinions and practice, diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him, and the whole body of Phyſicians at that time, yet uſed ſome method, and did not altogether ſwerve from the rules of Art, calls it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>a Methodical Hereſie.</hi> And finding others who obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no method, nor pretended to underſtand the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of things, or the natural cauſes of Diſtempers, but practiſed by ſome receipts which they had got, and which by uſe and experience they had found in ſome caſes to be very advantagious, and therefore boldly, though blindly, went on in ſo doing; this he calls <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>an Emperical Hereſie,</hi> or the Hereſie of Quacks and Empericks in that profeſſion. And in this ſenſe, we find the word uſed by Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; who by Hereſie do generally underſtand an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which is not agreeable to the Orthodox Faith; and whoſoever doth eſpouſe ſuch an Opinion, boldly teaching and obſtinately defending the ſame, is by them always reputed an Heretick.</p>
                     <p>Thus have I ſhown you the importance of the Word, and in what ſenſe it is uſed by Eccleſiaſtical Writers; and now I come to conſider the nature of the thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported thereby: which we may partly learn from ſuch as have written upon that Subject, but beſt from the Holy Scriptures. When Men entertain Opinions contrary to thoſe which the Catholick Church holds and believes, <hi>That is Hereſie,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> Fauſt.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And whoſoever,
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>de Definit.</hi>
                        </note> for the ſake of any temporal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and eſpecially for the advancement of his own Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Grandeur, doth forge and follow falſe and new Opinions, he is an Heretick, ſaith the ſame Holy Father.</p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152538:21"/>
                     <p>And whoſoever doth obſtinately defend that new Errour which he hath embraced,
<note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> he is an Heretick.</p>
                     <p>Hereſie is a kind of Infidelity,
<note place="margin">Th. Aq. 22. <hi>qu.</hi> 11. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi>
                        </note> belonging to them who profeſs the Faith of Chriſt, and corrupt the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines thereof, ſaith their Angelical Doctour.</p>
                     <p>Hereſie is converſant about thoſe things which are of Faith;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Idem ibid. art.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>viz.</hi> the Articles of Faith, and ſuch things as follow upon them, and conſiſts in an obſtinate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent therefrom, ſaith the ſame Doctour.</p>
                     <p>He that obſtinately believes what is contrary to the holy Catholick Faith,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 141. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note> is an Heretick, if he be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſaith their <hi>Navar.</hi> Doctour.</p>
                     <p>Whoſoever neglecting the authority of the Church,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Catech. ad Parochos, part.</hi> 1. <hi>in expoſ. art.</hi> 9. <hi>Symbol. p.</hi> 76. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note> doth defend wicked opinions with a wilfull and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate mind, is to be called an Heretick, ſaith the <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>And what we are to underſtand by the name of Church, the ſame Catechiſm afterwards informs us, and quotes St.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. n.</hi> 3. <hi>ad calcem.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49. for it, telling us, that by <hi>Church</hi> we are to underſtand the faithfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diſperſed through the whole world.</p>
                     <p>Though none of theſe will perhaps paſs for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Definition,
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>ad</hi> Quodvult Deum. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 2.</note> if examined according to the ſtrict rules thereof; nor it may be were ever intended as ſuch; (for as for St. <hi>Aug.</hi> he freely confeſſeth, That to expreſs by a regular Definition what Hereſie is, or what thing it is that makes an Heretick, in his judgment, is either impoſſible, or very difficult) yet may they paſs for good Deſcriptions, whence we may learn what notion they had of Hereſie in thoſe days, and what it was that in their judgment, did make a man an Heretick.</p>
                     <p>From St. <hi>Aug.</hi> we may learn that there are three things neceſſary to make up an Hereſie.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To believe ſuch things as are not believed by the Catholick Church:</p>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152538:21"/>
                     <p n="2">2. To broach thoſe falſe and new opinions, and thereby endeavour to make a party, for ſome ſecular advantage; eſpecially for the ſake of ones own glory and grandeur.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To defend thoſe falſe and new opinions with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy.</p>
                     <p>From their own Angelical Doctour we may learn, that there are four things neceſſary to make a man an Heretick.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He muſt be one that profeſſeth the true Faith.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He muſt corrupt the Doctrines of that Faith.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He muſt diſſent from ſome known eſtabliſhed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Faith.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. His diſſent muſt be maintained with obſtinacy.</p>
                     <p>From their <hi>Navar.</hi> Doctour we may learn that there are three things neceſſary to make an Heretick.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He muſt be one that is baptized, <hi>i. e.</hi> admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the memberſhip of Chriſt's Church, and who by himſelf or others, or both, hath made profeſſion of the holy Catholick Faith.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He muſt be one that hath embraced ſome falſe and new opinions which are contrary to that Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He muſt be one that doth believe and maintain thoſe falſe and new opinions with obſtinacy.</p>
                     <p>From their <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſm we may learn who may properly be called an Heretick.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He muſt be one that doth neglect and deſpiſe the Authority of the Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Authority which is neglected or deſpiſed by him muſt be the Authority of the Catholick Church diffuſive, <hi>Eccleſia eſt populus fidelis per univerſum orbem diſperſus,</hi> are the words of that Catechiſm, quoted out of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He muſt be one that holdeth and defendeth wicked opinions in deſpight and defiance of that Authority.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He muſt hold and defend thoſe wicked opinions with a wilfull and obſtinate mind.</p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152538:22"/>
                     <p>Thus far may we learn the nature of Hereſie from theſe Authorities, which are ſuch, as I ſuppoſe, our Adverſaries will not diſown; and if upon any of theſe ſeverally, or all of them joyntly, they think fit to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plead us, we are ready to join iſſue with them: and if by any of theſe they can make it appear that we are guilty, we do ſolemnly promiſe, that, by God's grace aſſiſting us, we will repent and amend; and I would willingly hope that they would be ſo ingenuous on their parts as to doe the ſame.</p>
                     <p>But before we proceed any farther, let us ſee what is more to be learn'd of the nature of Hereſie out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> tells them that <hi>there muſt be Hereſies among them,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> 
                        <hi>that they which are approved, may be made manifeſt.</hi> The riſe of which Hereſies is intimated in the verſe immediately preceding,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>V.</hi> 18.</note> where he ſaith, <hi>For firſt of all, when ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are diſſenſions among you,</hi> &amp;c. Diſſenſion is the firſt and greateſt evil, being the Source and Original of all others; for from thence proceed ſtrifes, debates, envyings, evil-ſpeaking, and all manner of contention; by means whereof the Unity of the Church is broken, her peace diſturbed, and her Members crumbled into parties and factions. Then doth every party ſet up for it ſelf, and for the ſake of its own glory and grandeur endeavours to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large its bounds, by alluring others to joyn with it. This it can never hope effectually to accompliſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having ſomething new to preſent them with; and therefore all Heads are at work to forge and foment ſome new and plauſible, though falſe opinion; which being once broached, muſt obſtinately be defended, and ſo commenceth Hereſie.</p>
                     <p>Thus we ſee the riſe and original of Hereſie, the dangerous and deſtructive conſequence whereof the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152538:22"/>ſame Apoſtle acquaints us with, who in his Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Galatia,</hi> reckoneth Hereſies among the works of the Fleſh, and tells us,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.</note> 
                        <hi>that they who doe ſuch things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And on this account is it, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives them that dreadfull Epithet, calling them damnable Hereſies. For, ſaith he,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> 
                        <hi>There were falſe Prophets alſo among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction.</hi> From this Text it is plain, that the Introducers of Hereſie, and the Ringleaders of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, are falſe Teachers; and theſe falſe Teachers in the time of the Goſpel, are compared to falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the time of the Law. To know therefore, and rightly underſtand, who thoſe falſe Prophets were, and what they did to deſerve that title; may poſſibly afford us ſome light, by which to diſcover thoſe falſe Teachers who privily bring in theſe damnable Hereſies; and not onely ſo, but in ſome meaſure alſo acquaint us with the nature of thoſe Crimes.</p>
                     <p>He who by ſigns and lying wonders ſought to turn away the People from the way,
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> which the Lord their God had commanded them to walk in, or perſwade them to pay their Religious Service and Worſhip to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Being, but onely the true God, was thereby known to be a falſe Prophet, not to be attended to, but ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
                     <p>Whoſoever ſhall preſume to ſpeak a word in the Name of God,
<note place="margin">Deut. 18.20.</note> which God hath not commanded him to ſpeak, or ſhall ſpeak in the Name of other Gods, the ſame is a falſe Prophet, and by the ſentence of Almighty God adjudged to death.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe who come unto you in ſheeps clothing,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.15. 1 Tim 4.2.</note> but inwardly are ravening Wolves. Who ſpeak lies in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared with an hot
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152538:23"/>Iron.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> Who have a form of Godlineſs, but deny the power thereof. They are falſe Prophets, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by us.</p>
                     <p>Thoſe who cauſe diviſions and offences,
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17, 18.</note> contrary to the Doctrine which we have learned, they ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Belly; and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the ſimple. Theſe are falſe Prophets or falſe Teachers, and ought to be marked and avoided by us.</p>
                     <p>Thus have I given you a ſhort Character of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets out of the Holy Scriptures, to whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> compares falſe Teachers in the time of the Goſpel: And by this you may eaſily diſcern them; for, if you find any at this day ſo teaching and ſo doing, as they then taught and did, you ought to mark them for falſe Teachers, and ſuch whoſe buſineſs it is to deceive you, and privily bring in damnable Hereſies.</p>
                     <p>But there is once place of Scripture more, in which we have a more particular account of the Nature of Hereſie, and from which we may more plainly learn what it is that makes an Heretick. And that is in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> where he gives him this direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.10, 11.</note> 
                        <hi>A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond admonition, reject: Knowing that he that is ſuch, is ſubverted, and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In this place St. <hi>Paul</hi> directs <hi>Titus,</hi> and not onely him, but all the Governours of the Church, how to deal with Hereticks; and inſtructs both them and us, what Hereſie is, and what it is that makes an Heretick.</p>
                     <p>Hereticks are to be dealt with in this manner, 1. They are to be admoniſhed, <hi>i. e.</hi> they are by the Governours of the Church to be warned to forſake that or thoſe errours which they have eſpouſed. For that they are in an Errour is implyed, otherwiſe there would be no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for an admonition, 2. That admonition is to be repeated, <hi>i. e.</hi> they are to be admoniſhed a firſt and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152538:23"/>ſecond time, 3. If they continue obſtinate after the firſt and ſecond admonition, they are to be rejected; <hi>i. e.</hi> the Cenſure of the Church is to paſs upon them, and they are thereby to be caſt out of the Society of Chriſtians, and avoided, leſt others ſhould be infected by them.</p>
                     <p>What Hereſie is, or what it is that makes an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, he likewiſe teacheth us, when he deſcribes the Heretical man he here ſpeaks of: 1. A man that is an Heretick, is one that is <hi>ſubverted, i. e.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> one that is gone aſtray, who hath turned aſide from the right path, forſaken and corrupted the true faith. Thus their own <hi>Lyra</hi> underſtands it, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Lyra <hi>in loc.</hi>
                        </note> A man that is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick is one, who having received the Catholick Faith, doth afterwards corrupt it.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gl. Ord. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud</hi> Lyr.</note> And with him the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Gloſs agreeth, telling us, he is an Heretick, who, by the words of the Law, oppoſeth the Law it ſelf; and puts his own ſenſe thereupon, that by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereof, he may ſtrengthen himſelf in the naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of his own mind. 2. A man that is an Heretick, is one that ſinneth, <hi>i. e.</hi> one that <hi>ſinneth</hi> knowingly,
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> ſaith the <hi>Int. Gl.</hi> Or as the word imports, one who is fallen from the way of Truth, and hath embraced the way of Errour; violently oppoſing the one, and as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately defending the other. 3. A man that is an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, is one that is <hi>condemned of himſelf.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> For that Faith which he once received and owned as true, he now oppoſeth and condemneth as falſe, ſaith <hi>Lyra,</hi> in <hi>Loc.</hi> Or becauſe he commendeth Errour, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Truth, ſaith <hi>Gl. Ord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Having thus conſidered both the importance of the word, and the nature of the thing I am treating of, I ſhall now adventure to lay down this ſhort, but full and comprehenſive Definition of it.</p>
                     <p>Hereſie is an Errour in the Foundation of Religion, openly taught, and obſtinately defended.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152538:24"/>
                     <p>I call Hereſie an Errour in Religion, to diſtinguiſh it from Philoſophical Errours; for thoſe, according to the ſtrict Eccleſiaſtical notion of the word, cannot fall under that Head. As alſo to difference it from Schiſm, for though Schiſm be an Errour, yet is it not properly an Errour in the Faith: It concerns not the Doctrine, but Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church; <hi>i. e.</hi> Manners, Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I call it an Errour in the Foundation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to diſtinguiſh it from Errours in the leſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable parts of Religion. For in ſpeculative points, ſuch as are matters of Controverſie, or mere School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niceties, relating to times or places, or other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Religion, not being plainly delivered in the word of God, nor can be proved thereby; Men may ſafely differ in their opinions, without incurring the Guilt of Hereſie. I ſay, this Errour muſt be openly taught, becauſe though men may be Hereticks, by eſpouſing ſome fundamental Errour, and tenaciouſly holding the ſame; Yet ſo long as they keep their opinion to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and do not endeavour to infect others there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, they are no Hereticks in the Eye of the Church. The Church can take no cognizance of their thoughts, nor paſs any Judgment upon them. In this caſe, they ſtand accountable onely to God, and their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Laſtly, I ſay, that this Errour muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with obſtinacy, to diſtinguiſh it from bare Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. For though a man be, (as all men are ſubject to be) in an Errour, yet if he be willing to be inſtructed, and, upon better information, to relinquiſh his Errour, he cannot be ſaid to be an Heretick.</p>
                     <p>Having thus ſtated the notion of Hereſie, I ſhall now proceed to conſider how far it is appliable to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and for this purpoſe I ſhall take the Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition in pieces, and conſider each part ſeverally.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152538:24"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Hereſie is an Errour in Religion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>It is an Errour in the foundation of Religion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. <hi>This Fundamental Errour muſt be openly taught.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>It muſt be obſtinately maintained.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. II. I. <hi>Hereſie is an Errour in Religion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THAT every Hereſie is an Errour, and an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in Religion, will be owned by all; but that every Errour, or every Errour in Religion, is He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, muſt not be granted; for Errour and Hereſie are not terms convertible. It will be neceſſary therefore to explain this part of the Definition; <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſee what it is we ſtand charged with, before we go about to diſcharge our ſelves of it.</p>
                     <p>By Religion here,
<note place="margin">Jude <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> I underſtand <hi>that Faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> and for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of which we are commanded earneſtly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; or that common Chriſtianity which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which we all do, or ought to profeſs and defend. And by Errour here, I underſtand an Opinion, which is contrary to, or at leaſt not agreeable with that Faith and common Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. Every Errour ſuppoſeth a Rule, and an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berration from that Rule: for what is Errour, but a wandring out of the right way, miſtaking one thing for another, eſteeming that falſe which is really true, or that true which is really falſe? Hereſie therefore being an Errour in Religion, muſt be a going aſtray
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152538:25"/>from that Rule, which the Author of our Religion hath given us to walk by. Now, who is the Author of our Religion but he who is ſtyled <hi>the author and finiſher of our faith,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> viz. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the righteous?</hi> And what ſtanding Rule hath he left us to go by,
<note place="margin">John 5.39. 2 Tim. 3.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> but only the holy Scriptures? Theſe, we are told, <hi>are able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation, and to make the man of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi> And what can we deſire more? Hereſie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be ſuch an Errour in Religion, as is againſt the truth of God's word, being neither contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor to be proved thereby. And whoſoever is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch an Errour, and proceedeth openly to teach, and obſtinately to defend the ſame, the whole guilt of Hereſie, and all the miſchievous conſequences thereof will lie at his door.</p>
                     <p>And now let us ſee how far this firſt part of the Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition doth affect the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Doth ſhe not embrace the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints? Is it not that which ſhe doth ſo earneſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for? doth ſhe not profeſs that common Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which ſhe hath received from Chriſt and his Apoſtles? doth ſhe not own <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to be the authour and finiſher of her Faith? and the holy Scripture to be the rule of her Religion? Doth ſhe teach any Doctrine that is not agreeable to the Word of God? or profeſs any Errour that is contrary to the Truth thereof? If ſhe do let her Adverſaries implead her, and if ſhe cannot defend her ſelf, ſhe will be ſo far from being obſtinate, that ſhe will readily own her fault, and, by God's aſſiſting grace, repent and reform. But if they cannot juſtly charge her with any of theſe things, let them for ſhame forbear their ungrounded clamour againſt her, as an Heretical Church.</p>
                     <p>The Innocency of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this point will manifeſtly appear if we conſider what ſhe doth publickly profeſs, and teach her Children to believe, in her Articles of Religion.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152538:25"/>
                     <p n="1">1. She doth declare her Belief,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note> That the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture containeth all things neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the three Creeds, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Nicene,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 8.</note> the <hi>Athanaſian,</hi> and that which is commonly called the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Creed, ought thoroughly to be received and believed; becauſe they may be proved by moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain warrants of holy Scripture.</p>
                     <p>And after ſuch a Declaration as this, with what face can the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> charge her with the guilt of Hereſie? The Church of <hi>England</hi> indeed is ſo modeſt, as not to challenge to her ſelf an Infallibility as that of <hi>Rome</hi> unwarrantably doth; She is willing to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that ſhe may err, but ſhe as firmly reſolves that ſhe will never be obſtinate in an errour, and therefore cannot be juſtly burdened with the guilt of Hereſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. III. II. <hi>Hereſie is an Errour in the Foundation of Religion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE Church of God is ſaid <hi>to be built upon the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note> 
                        <hi>Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner ſtone.</hi> Where, by the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, St.
<note place="margin">Lyr. <hi>in. loc.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> means (as their own <hi>Lyra</hi> informs us) the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets; the one foretelling, and the other preaching <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle tells us, That,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.10.</note> 
                        <hi>As a wiſe Maſter Builder he had laid the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152538:26"/>foundation, i. e.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lyra</hi>) the Faith of Chriſt, and none other; <hi>which Faith worketh by love.</hi> And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place he ſaith,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> 
                        <hi>The foundation of God ſtands ſure,</hi> i.e. ſaith <hi>Lyra,</hi> Fides Reſurrectionis, <hi>the Faith or Doctrine of the Reſurrection.</hi> Theſe Scriptures will help us to explain what we mean by the foundation of Religion in this part of the Definition, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome principal and fundamental point or points of Faith; or, as their own angelical Doctour ſtyles them,
<note place="margin">Th. Aq. 22. <hi>qu.</hi> 11. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi>
                        </note> ſome Article or Articles of Faith, or ſome Doctrines which neceſſarily follow therefrom. And by an Errour in this Foundation, I underſtand, not only a diſſenting therefrom, but alſo a making of ſomething to be Religion, or an Article of Faith which really is not ſo. And whether we be guilty of ſuch an Errour I leave to the impartial Reader to judge, when he hath carefully peruſed theſe Papers.</p>
                     <p>That the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not guilty of any ſuch Errour, methinks is very plain: For, ſhe doth publickly declare,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note> That whatſoever is not read in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (which contain the Doctrine of the Apoſtles and Prophets, and the Faith, or common Chriſtianity, which was once delivered to the Saints) nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to ſalvation. She alſo receiveth the three ancient Creeds,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 8.</note> and teacheth her Children to receive and believe every Article therein. And whilſt ſhe doth this, with what colour can the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> brand her with Hereſie, or charge her with an Errour in the foundation of Religion? A ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral charge without any particular inſtances will not doe, to ſuch an one this general anſwer may ſuffice; and when our Adverſaries think fit to deſcend to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars they may be further conſidered.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:152538:26"/>
                     <head>SECT. IV. III. <hi>This fundamental Errour muſt be openly taught.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE Church cannot, and therefore doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take cognizance of the thoughts of mens hearts; that is the ſole prerogative of Almighty God, who is the ſearcher of hearts and trier of reins. By the law of God a falſe Prophet or dreamer of dreams was to be ſlain, but then he muſt be ſuch an one as had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured thereby to ſeduce the people from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the true God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And our Saviour tells us of ſome who ſhould be called the leaſt in the kingdom of Heaven; <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhould have no place in the Church, but be caſt out of it as rotten and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound members. And that we may not be ignorant what ſort of men theſe are, he deſcribes them to us, telling us, They are thoſe who break his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and teach men ſo. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.19. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of ſome who <hi>ſhould privily bring in Damnable Hereſies,</hi> and theſe he calls <hi>Falſe Teachers,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1. And St. <hi>Pauls</hi> tells us of ſome who cauſed diviſions and offences in the Church, whom he warns us to avoid; but how ſhall we ſhun them unleſs we know them? He therefore gives us their character, telling us, they are ſuch as <hi>by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the ſimple. Rom.</hi> 16, 17, 18. Theſe inſtances may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently juſtifie this expreſſion, and ſhew you that it is not without cauſe that I have given it a place in the Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Hereſie. For, though a man have not only a kindneſs for ſome heretical opinions, or fundamental errours, but do heartily eſpouſe and embrace them; yet ſo long as he keeps all this lockt up in the cabinet
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152538:27"/>of his own breaſt, he is not cenſurable for it; nor can any one, without great raſhneſs, pronounce him an Heretick; for, not to be, and not to appear, <hi>in foro Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae,</hi> are the ſame. Hereſie then, which is ſo great and heinous a crime, an errour ſo miſchievous to the Church of God, and of ſo dangerous conſequence to the Heretick himſelf, ought certainly to be very well proved, and made mighty clear and manifeſt, before it be charged upon any man, or any ſociety of men who profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. For though every Hereſie be an Errour, yet every Errour is not Hereſie; It muſt be an Errour in Religion, and in the foundation of Religion too, and that fundamental Errour muſt be divulg'd and openly taught, <hi>i. e.</hi> there muſt be an endeavour to inſtill the poiſon of it into others, thereby to ſeduce and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw them from fundamental Truth and Holineſs; and all this muſt be own'd ſtoutly, and maintain'd obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, before it can merit the name of Hereſie.</p>
                     <p>Till therefore the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by plain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Arguments, hath proved all this particularly upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhe cannot without great raſhneſs and preſumption charge her with it. A general imputation, without particular proofs, will amount to no more than a malicious ſcandal, which will betray a great want of true Chriſtian charity in them, and the weight thereof will at laſt fall heavy upon their own heads.
<note place="margin">Alphonſus de Caſtro, <hi>de Haer. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 79.</note> For, as one of their own Doctours ſaith, Thoſe that ſo raſhly pronounce and call every thing Hereſie, not conſidering whereof they ſpeak, are often ſtricken with their own dart, and fall into the ſame pit that they themſelves had digged for others.</p>
                     <p>So far is the Church of <hi>England</hi> from openly teaching any fundamental errour in Religion, that ſhe neither is nor can be proved guilty of any ſuch, as is made appear in the preceding Section. She teacheth nothing but the pure Word of God, nor receiveth any thing as an
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152538:27"/>Article of Faith, or neceſſary to Salvation, but what is contained in holy Scripture, or may be proved thereby, and therefore cannot be juſtly charged with the guilt of Hereſie upon this account.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. V. IV. <hi>This fundamental Errour muſt be obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended and maintained.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THIS is the laſt part of the Definition, and that which gives ſpirit and life to all the reſt; for though we ſhould be guilty of Errour, and of Errour in Religion; yea though that Errour ſhould be a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental one, and openly taught by us; yet if we be not obſtinate therein, but upon fair and full conviction are willing to reform our Judgments, and relinquiſh the ſame, we cannot be juſtly burdened with the guilt of Hereſie.</p>
                     <p>Such is the modeſty of the Ch. of <hi>England,</hi> that ſhe doth not believe, much leſs boaſt her ſelf to be infallible, as the Ch. of <hi>Rome</hi> unwarrantably doth. As the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem, Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioch</hi> have erred, ſo ſhe, or any other particular Church may err; but ſuch is her piety and humility, that ſhe is very deſirous of, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to receive better information, and thereupon to reform and amend her Errours. She is, and ever hath been willing to ſubmit all her Doctrines to be tried by the touchſtone of God's Word, by the primitive Doctours and Paſtours of Chriſt's Church, and by the four firſt General Councils; and therefore, without great inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, cannot be thought to be obſtinate or contumacious.</p>
                     <p>To make a Fundamental Errour become Hereſie, two things you ſee are required.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>That Fundamental Errour muſt be defended.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>It muſt be defended with obſtinacy.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152538:28"/>
                     <head>SECT. VI. I. <hi>Of Defending a Fundamental Errour.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>TO be guilty of a fundamental Errour in Religion is a great and dangerous crime, but to perſiſt in it and undertake the defence of it, renders it yet greater and more dangerous; for Religion is that upon the due obſervance of which depends all our happineſs here, and all our hopes of happineſs hereafter; and therefore to miſtake therein, is like an errour in War, which is hard to be retrieved; but to go on in ſo doing, and ſet our wits upon the rack to invent arguments to maintain it, is to form weapons againſt our ſelves, with which to batter down all our hopes of future felicity. Yet even this may admit of ſome alleviation, for if thoſe who embrace thoſe errours be fully perſwaded that they are that Faith which was once delivered to the Saints, then are they obliged earneſtly to contend for them; or if in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof they do not contend ſo much for victory as for truth, being ready, upon better information, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh them; or if by the misfortune of an ill educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or otherwiſe, they be prepoſſeſſed therewith, and only hold them till they are better inſtructed, not being averſe to hearken thereto; ſuch an Errour, or ſuch a defence of it will not amount to Hereſie.</p>
                     <p>But, God be thanked, the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath no need of any excuſe in this caſe; for ſhe receiveth nothing as an Article of Faith, but what is contained in holy Scripture, nor defends any Doctrine but ſuch as may be proved thereby; and therefore it is a manifeſt injury, and malicious ſcandal in thoſe who charge her with the defence of any fundamental Errour in Religion. 'Tis true, ſhe contends earneſtly, but it is for the Faith that was once delivered to the Saints. She ſtrenuouſly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152538:28"/>defends the Religion which ſhe profeſſeth, but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath received it from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and becauſe it is well warranted by the Word of God. And if this be Hereſie, then is ſhe guilty of it; if not, then is ſhe unjuſtly charged with it by the Ch. of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VII. II. <hi>Of defending a fundamental Errour with Obſtinacy.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOW dangerous it is to eſpouſe a fundamental Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in Religion, and how much more dangerous it is to engage in the defence and maintenance of ſuch an errour, I have already told you; But if that defence be managed with ſtubbornneſs and obſtinacy, it renders the matter not only more dangerous, but very deſperate. <hi>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prov. 26.12.</note> 
                        <hi>there is more hope of a fool than of him,</hi> ſaith the wiſe <hi>Solomon.</hi> If a fool offend it is uſually out of ignorance, but the ſin of the other commonly proceeds from malice; a fool ſometimes will be counſelled, but he that is wiſe in his own conceit, ſhutteth both his eyes and his ears againſt all advice and inſtruction. And of ſuch St. <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaith well, They (<hi>i. e.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hilar. <hi>de Trin. l</hi> 6.</note> fools) foraſmuch as they know not the Truth, may have their ſalvation in ſafety, if afterward they believe; but all hope of ſalvation is ſhut from thee (<hi>i. e.</hi> who art wiſe in thy own conceit) becauſe thou denieſt that thing which thou canſt not chuſe but know. This is the caſe of him who obſtinately defends a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental errour in Religion; and it is this ſtubbornneſs and obſtinacy that doth complete and perfect his Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and by reaſon whereof he is juſtly ſtyled an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. But to make a man ſo obſtinate as to deſerve this title, two things are to be ſuppoſed; <hi>viz.</hi> Admonition and Conviction. 1. That he hath been admoniſhed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152538:29"/>and that more than once, of the evil of his way, of the danger of it, and of the neceſſity of leaving it. 2. That he is convinced in his own mind of all this. Theſe two are expreſly contained in that direction and advice which St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives to his Son <hi>Titus. A man that is an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition, reject; Knowing that he that is ſuch, is ſubverted,</hi> (or perverted) <hi>and ſinneth, being condemned of himſelf,</hi> Tit. 3.10, 11. Sec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore theſe two are ſo neceſſary to complete the character of an Heretick, it may not be amiſs to take a view of them ſeverally, before we apply the Character.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Of Obſtinacy in Errour againſt Admonition.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THAT men in Errour ought to be admoniſhed will be own'd by all, and that in caſe of Hereſie the Admonition is to be repeated, is plainly intimated by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his advice to his Son <hi>Titus,</hi> already quoted. And in what manner, and by whom this Admonition is to be given, our Saviour's Rule in the caſe of treſpaſſes and offences between brethren, will very fully inſtruct us;
<note place="margin">Matth. 18.15, 16, 17.</note> which is this. <hi>If thy brother treſpaſs againſt thee, go and tell him his fault between thee and him; if he hear thee thou haſt gained thy brother. But if he hear thee not, take with thee one or two; that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, every word may be confirmed. And if he refuſe to hear them, tell it unto the Church; and if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and a Publican.</hi> Where we may obſerve, that our Saviour ſpeaks of a twofold Admonition; <hi>viz.</hi> one that is to be given in private, and in a brotherly and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner; and another that is to be given in publick, by thoſe who had juriſdiction over the offending perſon,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152538:29"/>and are veſted with power and authority to cenſure him. Now let us apply this to the caſe in hand. If thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offend by embracing and tenaciouſly holding ſome fundamental errour in Religion, and this come to thy knowledge, it will be a charitable work in thee, if in a brotherly and friendly manner thou doſt privately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him between thee and him alone; if thou beeſt ſucceſsfull therein, thou haſt done a good work, thou haſt gained thy brother. But if this will not doe, thou muſt not leave it ſo, but take others with thee, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him before them. Thus far may a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon intereſs himſelf in admoniſhing another, who is faln into, or in danger of falling into Hereſie; and if the perſon admoniſhed continue obſtinate againſt ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, he doth by that ſtubbornneſs very much add to his crime, and incur the guilt of Hereſie; yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpeaking, he cannot truly be called an Heretick in the eye of the Church, becauſe ſhe hath not yet ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken cognizance thereof. And therefore it follows, if he refuſe to hear them, tell it to the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> bring the cauſe before them who have a juriſdiction over him, and ſufficient power and authority to cenſure and puniſh him. And being once and again admoniſhed by the Church, if he ſtill remain contumacious, then <hi>let him be rejected,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or as our Saviour here, <hi>let him be unto thee as an Heathen and Publican; i. e.</hi> let him by Excommunication be caſt out of the Church, and counted unworthy the ſociety of Chriſtian men.</p>
                     <p>This is the method in which we ought to proceed againſt Hereticks, they muſt be admoniſhed, and that Admonition muſt be repeated, and they muſt be obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate againſt that Admonition before we ought to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them. But it is not a private, but publick, not only a friendly, but authoritative Admonition, and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt that, which will truly denominate a man, or any Society of men to be Hereticks. For, Hereſie is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152538:30"/>an Opinion contrary to that of the Catholick Church,
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>cont.</hi> Fauſtum.</note> ſaith St. <hi>Aug.</hi> And whoſoever doth obſtinately believe that which is contrary to the holy Catholick Faith, is an Heretick,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>In Enchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 141. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note> if he be baptized, ſaith their <hi>Navar.</hi> Doctor. And whoſoever deſpiſing the authority of the Church, doth obſtinately defend wicked opinions,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>in expoſ. art.</hi> 9. <hi>Symbol. p.</hi> 76. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note> he is to be called an Heretick, ſaith their <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſm.</p>
                     <p>Now if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can prove that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath eſpouſed and publickly taught any fundamental Errour in Religion, and hath been thus regularly dealt withall, and duely admoniſhed by thoſe who had authority ſo to doe, and yet continued obſtinate in her errour againſt ſuch Admonition; then is ſhe guilty, otherwiſe not. But this I ſhall have Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſider more particularly hereafter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at preſent I ſhall proceed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Of Obſtinacy in Errour againſt Conviction.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AN Heretick is one that is not only ſubverted or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> but <hi>ſelf-condemned,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul: i. e.</hi> One who having once received and owned the true Faith, doth now oppoſe and condemn it as falſe, ſaith their own <hi>Lyra in loc.</hi> or one who commendeth Errour, and reproacheth truth, ſaith the <hi>Ord. Gl.</hi> Who like thoſe who accuſed the Woman taken in Adultery before our Saviour,
<note place="margin">John 8.9.</note> is convicted by his own Conſcience; <hi>i. e.</hi> who is conſcious to himſelf of the evil of his own doings. Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemnation always ſuppoſeth conviction; an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick therefore, being one that is ſelf-condemned, muſt alſo be convinc'd of the errour of his way; and one who notwithſtanding that conviction, ſtill remains ſtubborn and obſtinate therein; <hi>i. e.</hi> who reſiſts the repeated ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152538:30"/>of the Church. For, if a man labour under an invincible ignorance, and be thereby betrayed into ſome dangerous errour; or by the misfortune of an ill education have his judgment perverted and prepoſſeſſed with wrong notions and ſentiments of things, his caſe is truly pityable; and it would be very hard and injurious to burden him with the guilt of Hereſie. But if ſuch an one, being admoniſhed of the evil of his way, ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be convinc'd of his errour, and yet, after ſuch admonition and conviction contumaciouſly continue therein, he will have no plea left to excuſe him from the guilt thereof. By the old Law,
<note place="margin">Numb. 15.24, 25, 26, 27, &amp;c.</note> if a man ſinned through ignorance, there was an atonement provided for him; but if he ſinned preſumptuouſly, there was no atonement for him, but he was to be cut off from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people. This was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s caſe in the time of the Goſpel, for he himſelf tells us, That he was <hi>a blaſphemer, and a perſecutor, and an oppreſſor,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13.</note> 
                        <hi>but he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mercy, becauſe he did it ignorantly through unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi> But if after he was converted, he had been guilty of theſe crimes, his plea of ignorance and unbelief would then have been out of doors, and his caſe would have been very dangerous. <hi>For it is impoſſible,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 6.4, 5, 6.</note> 
                        <hi>that they who were once enlightened, and have taſted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, And have taſted of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come; If they fall away, that they ſhould be renewed again by repentance; ſeeing they crucifie again to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Son of God, and put him to open ſhame.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe Inſtances do plainly diſcover to us, that before conviction, though men be in errour, yea though it be a dangerous and fundamental errour, and induſtriouſly propagated by them, yet may their caſe be pityable; But when they are better informed, or at leaſt have means ſufficient for their better information; if after this they ſtill remain ſtubborn and contumacious in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152538:31"/>their errour, and perſiſt in the defence and propagation thereof; this their obſtinacy will alter the nature of their crime, and render their condition very dangerous if not deſperate.
<note place="margin">1 John 3.20, 21.</note> 
                        <hi>For if our heart condemn us, God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than our heart, and knoweth all things. But if our heart condemn us not, then have we boldneſs toward God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>John.</hi> And, <hi>Bleſſed is he who condemneth not himſelf in that thing which he alloweth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.22.</note> ſaith St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. X. <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>acquitted from the guilt of Hereſie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THIS notion of Hereſie, which hath been laid down and explained in the foregoing Sections, being not only Ours but Theirs alſo; being ſupported by ſo great and eminent Authorities, as that of St. <hi>Aug.</hi> of their own Angelical Doctour and canonized Saint, St. <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi> of their great <hi>Martin Navarrus,</hi> and of the moſt authentick Authority of their own Church at this day, the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in its Catechiſm <hi>ad Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chos:</hi> Our Adverſaries can have no colourable pretence to except againſt it. And if it be admitted, we are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to joyn iſſue with them, and contented to ſtand or fall by it. The point in difference between us is briefly this. <hi>Whether the guilt of Hereſie, according to this Notion, be juſtly or unjuſtly charged upon the Church of</hi> England <hi>by the Church of</hi> Rome? To acquit the Church of <hi>England</hi> is my task at preſent, in order whereunto I ſhall take a review of what hath been ſaid, and as brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as may be, apply it to our preſent caſe.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. If it cannot be proved that the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth receive, believe or teach any other Doctrine than what hath been received, believed and taught by the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152538:31"/>Catholick Church; nor broach any new Opinions, thereby to divide the Church for any ſecular advantage to her ſelf, nor obſtinately defend any falſe Opinions: Then, by St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s rule before quoted, ſhe cannot be juſtly charged with Hereſie: But none of all this ever was, or can be proved againſt her: And therefore, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, ſhe is unjuſtly taxed with Hereſie by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. If it cannot be made appear, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth corrupt the Faith which was once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Saints, nor teach any Doctrine contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, nor diſſent from any known eſtabliſhed Article thereof, nor obſtinately maintain any ſuch diſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from: Then, by the rule of their own Angelical Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, ſhe ought not to be charged with Hereſie: But none of all this ever was, or can be made appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her: Therefore, by this Rule, ſhe ought not to be charged with Hereſie by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. If it cannot be made manifeſt by any publick Act or Record owned as Authentick by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that ſhe hath renounced or forſaken that Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which ſhe was baptized, and of which ſhe once made profeſſion; nor embraced any falſe and new Opinions which are contrary thereunto; nor doth obſtinately believe and maintain any ſuch falſe and new Opinions; Then, by the Rule of their <hi>Navar.</hi> Doctour, ſhe cannot be juſtly charged with the guilt of Hereſie: But none of all this ever was, or can be made manifeſt againſt her: Therefore, by this Rule, ſhe is unjuſtly charged with the guilt of Hereſie by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. If it cannot be proved that the Church of <hi>England</hi> either doth, or ever did neglect and deſpiſe the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the holy Catholick Church; or doth embrace and hold any wicked Opinions in deſpight and defiance of that Authority; or with a wilfull and obſtinate mind, defend and maintain any ſuch wicked Opinions; Then,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152538:32"/>by the judgment of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm <hi>ad Parochos,</hi> ſhe ought not to be held guilty of Hereſie: But none of all this ever was, or can be proved againſt her: Therefore, by the Judgment of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, ſhe ought not to be held guilty of Hereſie.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. If there be not pregnant proof, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath embraced ſome Opinions, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to, or at leaſt not agreeable with that Faith and common Chriſtianity, which was taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; or hath laid a new foundation, <hi>i. e.</hi> made ſomething to be Religion, and an Article of Faith, which really is not ſo, being not built upon the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets; or doth openly teach any Fundamental Errours in Religion, thereby to ſeduce and withdraw people from fundamental Truth and Holineſs; or doth ſtubbornly maintain and defend a fundamental Errour in Religion againſt repeated Admonitions and clear Convictions: Then can ſhe not (if this Notion of Hereſie be true) be juſtly burdened with the guilt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But there is not, nor indeed can be any pregnant proof of any thing of all this againſt her: Therefore, according to this Notion of Hereſie, ſhe cannot be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged with the guilt thereof.</p>
                     <p>I am well aware that the Minor Propoſition in all theſe will ſtiffly be denied by our Adverſaries; they will with great boldneſs and confidence tell the world, that all this and more hath been, and ſtill may be proved againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But, God be thanked, though this may ſoon be ſaid it can never be proved. That they frequently call us Hereticks, and both do and have all along endeavoured to repreſent us as ſuch to the world, we very well know; and if they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be Judges it would go very hard with us, we ſhould not be able to acquit our ſelves at their Bar. But this we think to be a very unreaſonable thing, that they, being Parties, ſhould be Judges too; and therefore we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152538:32"/>appeal from them. And if they ask whither we do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal? I anſwer, we appeal to the Holy Scriptures, to the primitive Fathers, and to the four firſt General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. But becauſe this may ſeem to be either too tedious, or too troubleſome a way of trial, I have made choice of one more ſhort and eaſie; I have here laid down a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hereſie, which is agreed upon both by them and us, and therefore unexceptionable; by this we are willing to be tried, and by this to ſtand or fall.</p>
                     <p>I do not ſay in any of theſe Propoſitions, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver charged us with any of theſe things, for that I very well know they both do and have done; but I do ſay, that they neither have, nor ever can prove any of theſe things againſt us. And here now were a fit opportunity to examine the particulars of their charge, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of them; but before I do that, it will be requiſite to make good our own ground, and by giving you ſome account of theſe Propoſitions that either are, or will be denied, to make it appear that they are not the iſſue of a raſh and inconſiderate zeal, but the offspring of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and well digeſted thoughts. And though it be contrary to the Laws and Rules of Diſputation, to put one upon proving a Negative, and therefore I need not doe it; yet for once, and to gratifie our Adverſaries, I will endeavour to doe a work of Supererogation.</p>
                     <p>To make it appear that none of all theſe things have been by our Adverſaries proved againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> though it would be no very difficult, yet would it be a very tedious buſineſs. For to doe it effectually, I ſhould be obliged to examine not only all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their charge, but alſo the ſtrength or weakneſs of every Argument which they have at any time brought to make it good; which would take up ſo much time and paper as the deſigned brevity of this ſmall Treatiſe cannot allow. I ſhall therefore wave this, and inſtead thereof take a more ſhort and compendious, but every
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152538:33"/>way as effectual a courſe; It is acknowledged by all, that when an Adverſary is preſſed with an Abſurdity which he cannot eſcape, the Argument is concluſive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; If therefore I can make it appear that it is a thing impoſſible for our Adverſaries, according to their own Notion of Hereſie, to make good their charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of <hi>England;</hi> I may ſafely conclude that they have never done it, becauſe they could not doe that which is impoſſible to be done.</p>
                     <p>A thing is then ſaid to be impoſſible, either when it is ſimply and abſolutely ſo in it ſelf, or when it is ſo only upon ſuppoſition. It is then ſaid to be ſimply and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely impoſſible, when it implies a contradiction, or is altogether repugnant to the nature of the thing; as for inſtance: That one and the ſame Body, may be in more places than one, at one and the ſame time, is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſo repugnant and contradictious to the nature of Bodies, that he muſt be wilfully blind who doth not ſee an impoſſibility therein. A thing may be alſo ſaid to be impoſſible, upon ſuppoſition of an incapacity or inſufficiency either in the active or paſſive power, in the Efficient or Matter that is to be wrought upon. Though the thing be poſſible in it ſelf, yet if the Agent be not of ſufficient power to produce the effect deſigned, it is impoſſible upon that account. As for inſtance: if ten unarmed men ſhould undertake to beat ten thouſand well appointed and well diſciplined Souldiers in open field; it is poſſible indeed that thoſe ten thouſand may be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, but not by thoſe ten, becauſe they have not power ſufficient to doe it. Again, a thing may be ſaid to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible upon ſuppoſition of an incapacity in the paſſive power or matter that is to be wrought upon; for if the ſubject matter be wholly incapable of receiving ſuch an impreſſion, as the Agent would ſtamp upon it, though there may be no defect in the active power, yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the paſſive, there is an impoſſibility. Let us now apply this to the caſe in hand.</p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152538:33"/>
                     <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> chargeth the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the guilt of Hereſie, and the queſtion is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they can make good this charge againſt her? I do not queſtion the power of our Adverſaries to doe the thing, if it were to be done; but if it be not to be done, then, notwithſtanding the ſufficiency of their power, there is an incapacity in the ſubject they are to work upon which renders their attempt impoſſible. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do make it appear that it is impoſſible for them to prove this againſt us, it will be a fair Juſtification of the Minor Propoſition in all the foregoing Arguments, and conſequently a clear diſcharge of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from that foul aſperſion ſo unjuſtly caſt upon her by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now this I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make good in this manner.</p>
                     <p>The Notion of Hereſie here laid down, I have made appear to be that which is allowed by them as well as us, and therefore that muſt be the Standard we are to be tried by. Their work therefore will be, to make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that there are ſome Doctrines received, believed and taught by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which are Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the foundation of Religion, and thoſe obſtinately defended and maintained by her. Now the only way to know what Doctrines are received, believed and taught by any Church, or Society of Chriſtians, is, to have recourſe to the publick Acts, and authentick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of that Church or Society; and that is no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult task, for ours are made publick and expoſed to the view of all. And if they know not what we own as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Records, I ſhall here inform them. 1. The Holy Scripture is the foundation of our Faith, and the Rule of our Religion. 2. The 39 Articles agreed upon by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of both Provinces, and the whole Clergy, in the Convocation holden at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1562, which are partly Poſitive and partly Negative; where they declare the Faith and Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they are poſitive; and where
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152538:34"/>they reject the Additions, Alterations and Innovations of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they may be termed Negative. 3. The Book of Homilies, wherein the Doctrines of our Church briefly declared in the Articles, are more largely explained. Theſe are the publick Acts and authentick Records wherein the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are to be found,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note> for ſhe publickly declares, That all things neceſſary to Salvation are contained in the Holy Scripture, and that whatſoever is not read there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salvation. She alſo declares,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 8.</note> That the three Creeds, the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Creed, and that which is commonly called the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Creed, ought thoroughly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and believed; for they may be proved by moſt certain warrants of Holy Scripture. Unleſs therefore our Adverſaries can find Hereſie in the Holy Scripture, or in the Articles of Faith ſummarily contained in the three ancient Creeds, it will be impoſſible for them to find it in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe ſhe doth not receive, believe or teach any other Doctrine but what is contained therein, or may be proved thereby. This is that Faith and common Chriſtianity which we received from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and which we reſolve (by God's grace) to hold faſt. This is that which hath been always held and taught by the <hi>One Holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Church.</hi> This is the foundation upon which our Religion is built, <hi>viz.</hi> upon the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> himſelf being the chief corner ſtone. And therefore unleſs they can ſhake this Foundation, unleſs they will impeach Chriſt and his Apoſtles, unleſs they will charge the whole Church of God with the guilt of Hereſie; all their attempts and batteries level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt us will be vain and fruitleſs. The Church of <hi>England</hi> will ſtill ſtand like a Rock, againſt which thoſe waves may break themſelves, whilſt ſhe remains unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them.</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152538:34"/>
                     <p>Thus, you ſee, how impoſſible it is for our Adverſaries to make good their charge againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and if they cannot doe it, we may ſafely conclude they have not done it; and if they neither have, nor can doe it, then is it a foul aſperſion by them unjuſtly caſt upon us. For which their unjuſt, uncharitable and unchriſtian cenſure, I pray God forgive them.</p>
                     <p>Having thus ſecured that Poſt which was moſt likely to be attacqued by the Enemy, I ſhall now take the boldneſs to make a ſhort Sally upon them; and take an account of their ſtrength, by conſidering ſome of the moſt material Arguments which have been offered by their Champions to make good their charge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> (as I find him cited by Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in the defence of his Apology, <hi>p.</hi> 2.) makes ſhort work of it, and very magiſterially doth at once determine the whole matter. For (ſaith he) <hi>Whoſo denieth the privilege and ſupremacy of the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>hath renounced the Faith, and is an Heretick.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Major. &amp; Obed. unam San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam. Diſt.</hi> 22. <hi>Omnes.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer, 1. If the privilege and ſupremacy of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> be an Article of Faith, we deſire to know in which of the three Creeds, or in what part of the Bible we may find it, for we would not willingly be wanting in our compliance with any Article of Faith. 2. If this be ſo, then the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> conſiſting of 630 Biſhops and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers gathered together from all parts of the world, was a pack of Hereticks, for they gave equal privileges to the See of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with that of <hi>Rome.</hi> 3. If this be ſo, then Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the great (and I take him to be altogether as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible as Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi>) was an Heretick, for he calleth him who uſurps ſuch an arrogant ſtyle, the forerunner of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi> 4. If ſubjection to the ſee of <hi>Rome</hi> be a neceſſary part in the Definition of Hereſie, then all the Chriſtians in the world, except thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; for all of them, as well as we, do unanimouſly oppoſe the Supremacy of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Their Angelical Doctour, and Canonized Saint, S. <hi>Tho. Aquinas,</hi> thus argueth.
<note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 11.2.3.</note> 
                        <hi>When a matter is once determined by the Authority of the Catholick Church, if any one ſhall obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately gainſay ſuch Determination, he is to be reputed an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, which Authority</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth principally reſide in the Pope.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Argument is founded upon ſeveral falſe Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Catholick Church,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152538:35"/>which we cannot conſent to, becauſe we cannot believe that a part is the whole. 2. That the Determinations of that Church are obligatory to all other Churches. This we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree with him in, becauſe <hi>Par in parem non habet imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> Equals have no authority over one another. 3. That the Authority of the Catholick Church is principally lodged in the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> This we cannot believe, becauſe we have no warrant for it, either from the Holy Scriptures, or from the four firſt General Councils, or from any authentick Antiquity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. <hi>Proteſtants are Hereticks, becauſe they oppoſe divers Truths propounded for divine by the viſible Church</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Argument is alſo ſupported by theſe falſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions: 1. That to oppoſe any Truth propounded by the Church, is Hereſie; This we deny: We grant indeed that to oppoſe any Truth, howſoever or by whomſoever propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is an Errour; but it cannot be called an Hereſie, unleſs it be ſuch a Truth as is an Eſſential part of the Goſpel of Chriſt. 2. That the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Proteſtants are divine-Truths. This we take to be a falſe Suppoſition, for we do not oppoſe any Truth, much leſs any divine Truth that is held by them, but only ſuch falſe and new invented Articles as are by them ſuperadded to the Catholick Faith. 3. That whatſoever is propounded by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is propounded by the viſible Church. This we cannot allow, becauſe we know that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is but a part, and, God knows, a corrupted part too, of the viſible Church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. <hi>The viſible Church is Judge of Controverſies, and therefore Infallible; To oppoſe her therefore is to oppoſe God. This Proteſtants doe, and therefore are guilty of Hereſie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is here taken for granted, 1. That the viſible Church is Judge of Controverſies. 2. That ſhe is Infallible. 3. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is this viſible Church. 4. That to oppoſe her is to oppoſe God. All which Suppoſitions are matters of Diſpute between us and yet undetermined, and therefore very inſufficient grounds to build ſuch a charge upon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. <hi>Want of Succeſſion of Biſhops and Paſtours holding al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſame Doctrine, and of the Forms of Ordaining Biſhops and Prieſts which are in uſe in the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, is a certain mark of Hereſie. But Proteſtants want all theſe things. Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> We deny the Major. For, 1. Nothing but want of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152538:35"/>Truth, and holding Errour, can make or prove a Man or Church to be Heretical. 2. Becauſe it is not a Succeſſion of Perſons, but of Doctrine, that can ſecure a Church from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. And to ſuch a Succeſſion there are two things neceſſary. 1. That there be an agreement with the Apoſtles Doctrine. 2. That there be an uninterrupted conveyance of it down to them who challenge it: Both which we have.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. <hi>Proteſtants have forſaken a Church confeſſedly very ancient, and beſides which there could be demonſtrated no other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church of Christ upon earth. Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer, 1. That againſt God and Truth there lies no preſcription, and therefore it is great wiſedom to forſake ancient Errours for more ancient Truths. 2. That there are many other viſible Churches of Chriſt upon earth beſides the <hi>Roman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe are the moſt material Arguments I have yet met with, by which our Adverſaries have attempted to make good their charge of Hereſie againſt us; and how rotten a foundation theſe are to build ſuch a mighty Superſtructure upon, I ſhall now leave to the impartial Reader to judge. And becauſe I deſign brevity, and am unwilling to draw out this diſcourſe to too great a length, I ſhall now haſten to a concluſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="conclusion" type="section">
                     <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
                     <p>IN this Diſcourſe I have laid down ſuch a Notion of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as is generally received and owned by our Adverſaries themſelves, and by that have ſtrictly examined the Charge which they bring againſt us, and I hope have made it very plain and manifeſt, That the imputation of Hereſie to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is a ſoul aſperſion, and cannot without great injuſtice be caſt upon Her. Which is the only thing I have undertaken to make good in this ſhort Treatiſe.</p>
                     <p>I am heartily ſorry that there ſhould be any occaſion for a Diſcourſe of this nature, I am a great lover of Peace and Truth, and do greatly abhor both Schiſm and Hereſie; by the former of which the Church's peace is diſturbed, and her Members crumbled into parties and factions; and by the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which her Truth is fullied, her Doctrine perverted, and the whole frame of Religion put out of order. And therefore I do earneſtly pray (as my dear Mother the Church
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152538:36"/>of <hi>England</hi> hath taught me) that all thoſe who have erred and are deceived, may be brought into the way of truth, and that Unity, Peace and Concord may flouriſh in all Nations. I have no pleaſure in ſtrife and debates, and if I were not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to contend earneſtly for the Faith, which was once delivered to the Saints, ſhould be very unwillingly drawn to engage in them. But when I meet with a loud and unground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed clamour, branding thoſe who embrace, and endeavour to hold faſt the holy Catholick Faith, with the odious names of Schiſmaticks and Hereticks, I cannot forbear according to my poor ability, to ſtand up in the defence of injured In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and abuſed Truth. This is that which I did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and have attempted to doe, in both the Parts of this diſcourſe; and if our Adverſaries be angry with me for it, I cannot help it, nor am I much concerned at it. But if through weakneſs or inadvertency, I have failed in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or not defended the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo well as I ought, and as one more able might have done, from thoſe foul Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions, which have been ſo unjuſtly caſt upon her, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg her pardon, and do freely ſubmit both my ſelf and undertaking to her cenſure, well knowing, that ſhe is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Mother, and will put a favourable conſtruction up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what was well meant.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall conclude all with a paſſionate intreaty, and earneſt requeſt, both to thoſe of the <hi>Roman,</hi> and thoſe of our own Communion, that they would all devoutly joyn with me in this humble and hearty prayer to Almighty God,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>From all Sedition, privy Conſpiracy and Rebellion; from all falſe Doctrine, Hereſie, and Schiſm; from hardneſs of Heart, and contempt of thy Word and Commandment,</hi> [Good Lord deliver us.]</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
                  <p>SOme Queries to Proteſtants Anſwered. And an Explanation of <hi>Roman. Catholick's</hi> Belief in Four Great Points conſidered. 1. Concerning their <hi>Church.</hi> 2. Their <hi>Worſhip.</hi> 3. <hi>Juſtification.</hi> 4. <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo lately printed, <hi>A Seaſonable Proſpect for the View and Conſideration of Chriſtians. Being a brief Repreſentation of the Lives and Converſations of</hi> Infidels <hi>and</hi> Heathens, <hi>as to Religion and Morality in our Age. Together with ſome Reflexions thereupon, in Relation to us who profeſs Chriſtianity.</hi> Written by a Gentleman. Both Printed for <hi>Luke Meredith</hi> at the King<hi>'s</hi> Head in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
